<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise againste the preuee masse in the behalfe and furtheraunce of the mooste hylye communyon made by Edmund Gest. Reade gentyll reader and then iudge. M. D. XLVIII.</title>
            <author>Gest, Edmund.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01664</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11802</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110813</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846284</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846284</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11242</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01664)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11242)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 45:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise againste the preuee masse in the behalfe and furtheraunce of the mooste hylye communyon made by Edmund Gest. Reade gentyll reader and then iudge. M. D. XLVIII.</title>
                  <author>Gest, Edmund.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[180] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In saynt Andrewes Paryshe, in the Waredrop. By [William Hill and] Thomas Raynald,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1548.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page varies: line 4 has misprint: "hylye" or is corrected to: "holye"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Additonal printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Private masses --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11242:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11242:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Treatiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte the preuee Maſſe in the behalfe and furtheraunce of the mooſte hylye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munyon, made by Edmund Geſt</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Reade gentyll reader and then iudge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M.D.XLVIII</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Cum Priuilegio ad Imprimendum Solum.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſaynt Andrewes Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe, In the Waredrop. By Thomas Raynald.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:11242:2"/>
            <p>¶ Fautes eſcaped by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> printer, reade in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſyde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt leafe &amp;, xiiii. line of b, exhibitiue for exhitiue, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrd leafe &amp; ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſyde &amp; fourth line rede, not bread for bread, &amp; in the fourthe leafe &amp; laſt lyne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſyde, rede and for er, &amp; in the fyft leafe &amp; fyrſt ſyde &amp; .xviii. lyne rede geuing ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes for ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes gyuen &amp; in the, vi, leaf fyrſt ſyde &amp; ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d lyne, rede leſt for eſt, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſyde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame leafe &amp; .x. lyne rede of for yf, &amp; in the .xiiii. line ſeable for feble, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vii. leafe fyrſt ſyde &amp; xvii. line, rede auouch for whych, &amp; in the laſt leaf &amp; ſyde, reade Baptiſme for baptiſe, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xiiii. line termed for turned.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11242:2"/>
            <head>To the righte worſhipful maiſter Cheke, ſcole maiſter to the Kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and prouoſt of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy colledge in Cambridge, Edmund Geſt wyſheth enteir health both of body and ſoule.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot wythſtandynge (ryght worſhipfull) I haue attempted an en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terpryce in prouynge eche parcel of the pryuye maſſe to dyſpleaſe god, whiche I can ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word, matier, ne reaſon accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynglye, and ſo am rather dyſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked then lyked of manye for thys my doyng, rather heady then hee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy as they ſuppoſe: Howebeyt in caſe the ſayd perſons woll wythe me earneſtly reſpect my bounden
<pb facs="tcp:11242:3"/> deutie in the ſayd doyng, they (I doubte not (woll be rathere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented then diſconte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with me for the ſame. For why? it is godes oppen wyll that not they alone, whom he hath mercifully delyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red ten or fyue talentes vnto,<note place="margin">Mat. xxv.</note> but they alſo, who haue freelye recea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued at hys mercye handes, but one talent, ſhuld occupy the ſame, to hys moſt auauntage, &amp; not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrappe it (to his great hinderan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce) in a napkyn. Leſſe he wolde therfore withdraw it from theim, and delyuer it to the well occupy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers, either of the fyue or ten talen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes heretofore eſpecyfied (A clear enſample wherof is for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning recorded i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Math. xxv) By re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof, albeit I am but ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowledged i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcriptur matters in reſpect of others, whoſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is ten or fyue talentes too myne one, &amp; ſo am not hable to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uale and gane therwith any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:11242:3"/> ſo much, as they w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thers, who ar paſſingly ſkylled in the mattiers before ſaid: This not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g I muſt occupy my talent &amp; auan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ſo much therby vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, as I can poſſyble, to the full diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my bonden dew herin, otherwiſe ſtraitely charged with al.<note place="margin">luke. xvi.</note> For we muſt all become accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dreadful lord for our receipt &amp; ſtewardſhip.<note place="margin">luke. xvi</note> Who ſo ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th Chriſte,<note place="margin">Math. 14.</note> is not faithful in a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is not truſty i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moch. We muſt al be buſely occupied tyl he come, eche man in his call accordyngly No man muſt attempt to appear before hym whithoute hys offre,<note place="margin">Deut. xvi.</note> more or leſſe, according to his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes herein, which he eſtemeth, and not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value &amp; bygnes of the offredge.<note place="margin">luke. 21.</note> Though the ſely poore wydowe offred but two mytes in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes cheaſt, yet was ſhe no leſſe regarded of hym therfor, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great rych men, who offred in
<pb facs="tcp:11242:4"/> to the ſame much more. Eche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſayeth Hierome) offreth in to the lordes houſe what he can, Some golde, ſyluer &amp; <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>cyous ſtone, So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me eyther goteſkinnes, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the ſame. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord nedeth all theſe, And he is egally pleaſed with them, who haue vnegally o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffrede. In reſpecte wherof I haue offred vnto hym, this my ſymple poor myte or goate heare, truſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g he wol of hys mercye, both accept y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, &amp; occaſion hereby others, to wryte more groundely &amp; clerk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thys matteir, whych I haue choſen rather then an otheyr too e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treate vpon, In reſpecte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treate therof is both right avaylable &amp; nedefull to hys churche, &amp; ſo ava<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageable to him ſelue, In y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth much to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcontinuance &amp; owerthrowe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryuat maſſe, wherin we are moſt piteouſly blin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great dyſworſhipe bothe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:4"/> of our ſauyour &amp; hys moſte holy communyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This myne attempt (which as ye ſe, not of pride but of mere conſcience I am e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forced to) not wythſtandynge I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to the lorde: Houbeit I enſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayſe worthy vſage of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers herein doo offre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to ſom other beſide, namely to your worſhipful maſterſhip, not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iudge it a <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, worthy your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wold hereby ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my poore harte toward your mayſter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyp, truſtyng ye of your wonted vnſpekeable ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlenes wol take it in good parte, not reſpectynge ſo muche the vylenes therof, as the good mynde of the preſenter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, who (vndoubtedly) hath <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented, not all what he willyngly wolde, but what hym hably could theyrin. And thus I betake ye to god, whom I moſt enteirly be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſech to enuiron you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys grace
<pb facs="tcp:11242:5"/> ſo to tread y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kinges maieſte i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all vertue, wiſdome, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, as ſhalbe, fyrſte to the hygh contentacion of god ſelue, &amp; furtherance of hys trueth, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to the Kinges honour and weale of hys realmes, laſtelye too youre greate worſhyppe name and furtheraunce A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11242:5"/>
            <head>To the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an Reader euerlaſtynge gretynge in the Lorde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Volde god (dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re reader) ſoch a per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon had attempted, and attempted, had perfected, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, had openly publyſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthy diſcloſe and diſproue of the vnſufferable abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the popyſſhe priuate pryuye maſſe, an enterpryſe no leſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deful than auayleable at al ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons, and for all perſonnes, and namely at thys preſent, whyche is, thanke be vnto the lord God, ſo fauourable and benefyciall to the furthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the goſpell truth, and ſo preiudicial &amp; hurt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:11242:6"/> to the hinderance of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: who for hys worthy know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege perfectly knew, worthely &amp; conninglye, for hys hartie zeale wolde earneſtlye, for hys bolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes durſt openly, and for his elo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quence wold eloquently, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly handel, and diſcouer the ſayd vngodlynes, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kemanly paynt the ſame before thyne eyes. For why as it is ryghte conuenable &amp; behouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that as eche vngodlye, and exchueable vice, ſo the hertofore mencyoned ydolatrie, or ymage worſhyppe muſt of force be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, and ſenſyblye dyſcloſed, not onely for that it is a doying both haynouſe and wycked, but by reaſon it is alſo pretenſed &amp; cloked, wtyh the pretence and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped
<pb facs="tcp:11242:6"/> name of the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelicall truthe, &amp; recompted in maner of eche man, (thee more pytye) for the worthyeſt vertue, and for a worſhyp not to man alone, but to God alſo, mooſte ſeruiceable and acceptable. To murder a gyltleſſe perſonne, is a defaulte full greuouſe, and thy ſelfe beſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, moch more greuouſe, but not thy ſelfe alone, and an other but a greate compaignye of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes wythall, that is mooſte gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſe of al. What ſayd I mooſt greuouſe? Noo not ſo. For thee ſayde murder compared wythe the ſlaughter of one poore ſeely ſoule, is in reſpecte thereof, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge greuouſe at all, By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as one ſoule ſourmounteth,
<pb facs="tcp:11242:7"/> and paſſeth in worthines an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fynite number of bodies, ſo the ſlaughter of one ſoule is more greuouſe, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the murder of an vnnumerable ſorte of bodyes: Howbeit the murder of ſondrie ſoules is more greuouſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one, &amp; ſo conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of an infinite ſorte is paſſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge greuouſe In reſpect wherof, Oh what a greuouſe cruel dede is our ſolytary and alone maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge, whych doeth murder not the bodies alone (a wycked and a cruel dede), but which is moſt greuouſe and wycked of al) the ſoules alſo, not for a tyme, but for euer: not to be without plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure and greuance, but to be in endeles wofulnes, not of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn of the worſhippers &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teners therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but of eche one wythout reſtraynt, onleſſe he in
<pb facs="tcp:11242:7"/> tyme become repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tant, whether he be a pryue maſſer or a pryua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te maſſe helper, whether he bee an hartie hearer or proctour of the ſayd maſſe,<note place="margin">Roma. 1</note> ſo that in effecte he be a ſolytarye maſſe worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, for as S. paule auoucheth not euyll workers alone, but theyr approuers and mayntey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for that they be lyke myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhalbe lyke punyſhed, Yf the eatyng of an apple in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſe dyd worthely and merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlye ſlaye as queſtionles it dyd not bodely only, but ghoſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly alſo, not Adam alone but his wyfe alſo, &amp; not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone but al theyr poſterite, and that not for a tyme, but euerlaſtinglye, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was directely agaynſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commandemente of god, otherwyſe beyng nothing dero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatorye to God or preiudiciall
<pb facs="tcp:11242:8"/> to man: Certaynlye then oure alone maſſynge, for ſo moch as it is not onelye a breache of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des open and holye commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente, as the eatynge of thee inhibited forbydden apple was, but an open ymage worſhyp al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and a forged made ſeruice of god, whych is a default, no leſſe haynouſe than the ſayd breache, yea, and more too: doeth moche more murder, aſwel ghoſtely as bodely, not onelye the doers and kepers of thee pryuate Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, but thee vpholders alſo, and worſhyppers there vpon, onleſſe they hartelye, and that in thys preſente lyfe repent them ſelues for the ſame. For a double fault, deſerueth a double death a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dampnatyon aſwell of thee as
<pb facs="tcp:11242:8"/> agreers and fauourers thereof, as of the authors, and doers, of the ſame, Is it not a wicked doy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge to endamage an innocente bodye? and is it not a myſdede moche more wycked, to murder the ſame? yes verely. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyles here vpon gatherable, it is oure alone maſſing is a wycked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes vncomparable, By reaſon therein Chriſtes bodye, whyche paſſynglye ſurmounteth all bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delye creatures, bothe in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynes dignitie, and in acceptan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce wythe Godde is aſſayde daye by daye of thee alone Maſſers, to be mortefyed &amp; done to death. In conſideration (wherof) good Chriſtian reader, I beſeche thee by the precyouſe deathe of oure alone Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braſe lowe and frequent onelye,
<pb facs="tcp:11242:9"/> the moſt ſacred co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes owne ordynaunce the true maſſe, the true ſacrament exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiue of chriſtes body &amp; bloud, the verye ghoſtely nurryture &amp; foode both of oure bodyes and ſoules, into lyfe euerlaſtynge, &amp; vtterly eſchue auoyde, &amp; deteſte the pryuate maſſe, thee vſurped and falſe named communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or maſſe, the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed &amp; conterfayte ſacrament, mans ordynaunce &amp; tradycyon, the preſente poyſon both of our bodies and ſoules, into death not temporal alone, but eternal alſo. What is ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge that vnſyttyng haynouſe and abhominable vyce, but an embecilmente and ſtelthe of an holy thing out of an holy place, whych is adiuged the more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ful haynouſe and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble in reſpect of thee more holye
<pb facs="tcp:11242:9"/> thynge embecilled, and ſtollen out of the more holy place wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vpon it formally argueth oure pryuate maſſing is a ſacriledge mooſt vnſytting, haynouſe and deteſtable. For aſmoch as it is a ſtelth of holye thinges, not of the baſeſt ſute as candelſtickes ſencers, croſſes and chalices be, but of the holyeſt and chiefeſte kynde, namely of chriſte, of the holy ghoſt, of true relygyon, of fayth, of godlynes, repoſed and placed not in a ſtony temple or aulter but in a chriſtian &amp; faith, ful hart which is iuſtly eſtemed more preciouſe and holy than a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtone te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pels or aulters whych after thee report of paul is the temple of the holy ghoſte &amp; the manſyon place of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed trynitie,<note place="margin">i, Cor, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Iohan, 14</note> as chriſte hym ſelfe wytneſſeth in Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The more
<pb facs="tcp:11242:10"/> preciouſe marriage, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more hay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nouſe default is the breach ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of. What marriage is in worthy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to be compared wyth the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall marryage, that is betwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne chriſt and vs? Verely none at all, By reaſon wherof our alone maſſinge muſte remedileſſe be a mooſt haynouſe treſpace, For that it diſſeuereth the ſayd mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and enforſeth vs to whore with falſe goddes agaynſt chriſt the lyuinge God oure ſpirituall huſbande. Oh Lorde what an vnſpeakeable and vncompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vyce is thee Pryuee Maſſe. In caſe ſhe dyd but murder me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſoules &amp; bodies ſhe were to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but ſythe ſhe atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pteth thee, ſlaughter of the bleſſed bodye of chriſt, ſythe ſhe embecilleth &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out of our hartes chriſt the holy ghoſt, &amp; theyr body &amp; ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:11242:10"/> ſauing frutes, ſithe ſhe fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dereth and diuorſeth the marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene chriſt &amp; vs: ſhe muſt no re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medy be vncomparably &amp; vnſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keably wycked. Is it not a lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table fyght, to behold how hygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly men eſteme this pryuate maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe whych mothereth ſo manyfol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and haynouſe vyces? Is it not great pytye to ſee how ſhe is ſuffered and frequented emon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſte vs? Is it not a deadely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe to reſpect the worthy cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes in thys realme, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate number of them, and yet not one to wryte agaynſte hyr? Who yf they wold, could handle &amp; vtter hyr accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly? Yeas truli. Wel ſythe they (who perfectly ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) wyl not wryte agaynſt the ſayd maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, ſythe it is nedefull, that her ſynfulnes to longe dyſſembled, ſhoulde be openly vttered, ſythe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:11"/> ſythe I am enforced in conſcien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce in thys greate vnſeaſonable ſylence emong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great dyuines in this behalf, to declare my ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macke agayn here, I wil by god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des grace vndertake to wrytte agaynſt the hertofore mencyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned maſſe, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding I am nothing fyt or ſuffycient to the ful perfourmaunce of ſo greate an enterpryſe occaſyoned ſo to do,<note place="margin">luke. 23</note> through this the ſayinge of chriſt, yf my dyſciples wyl hold theyr peace the ſtones ſhal ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke wherby he doeth vs to wyt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, it is hys wyl &amp; prouidence that whan the learned refuſe to ſette forth hys truthe, the vnlearned ſhulde further and promote it? Better it is ſomewhat to wryte and enueyghe agaynſt the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſhe maſſe, and that groſly tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſo godly nothing at al. Bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:11242:11"/> it is that the rude ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple ſhuld by my talke perceaue ſomwhat of the ſinfulnes of the ſayd maſſe, than through my ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lence nothynge at all, Better it is that the ſayd people ſhuld be ſomewhat wythdrawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr receaued maſſe errour, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they ſhuld wholy after theyr ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>coſtumed wonte endure in thee ſame. In reſpect wherof that what I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſible deuiſe to the vttera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and reprofe of the faultes incide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to thee pryuate maſſe eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now by gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance do I wryte. Therfore good reader gyue heedy attendaunce therto:</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11242:12"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ryue maſſe after the doctryne of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe boke entituled Antididagma is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyoned of fowre par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, namelye of thee Sacryfyce of Chriſtes bodye and bloude, of the receypt of the communion of prayer, and of doctryne. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe partes orderly wyl I declare and conferre them wyth goddes wrytten worde, vpon the confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and tryall whereof it ſhall (I doubt not) appeare ful true that eche parcel of the pryuate maſſe is vngodlye, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the maſſe ſelfe, exceadynge vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godlye.</p>
            <p>The fyrſte parte of the ſayd maſſe is thee ſacryfyce wherun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to be incydente alwaye conſecra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:11242:12"/> tranſubſtanciation and the worſhippe of Chriſtes body and bloude. And by reaſon conſecra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon for goethe tranſubſtancia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and tranſubſtanciation the ſacryfyce, and the worſhyppe af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tergoethe them all: I wyll fyrſte talke vpon conſecratyon, and them orderly vpon the remnaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecracyon is that percel of the maſſe, wherein thee prieſt pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumeth, to conſecrat and hallow Chrſtes bodye and bloude. The whyche, as it is an attempte too vnreaſonable and vnable ſo paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge wycked preſumptuouſe &amp; deteſtable. For howe can it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble be that chriſtes bodye whych cannot be made holyer and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecter tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> already it is: ſhuld or myght be conſecrat of the prieſt? Thys muſte nedes be that / that
<pb facs="tcp:11242:13"/> is hallowed was before his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, eyther throughly pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phane &amp; nothing holy at al, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther elſe not ſo holy, in conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racyon wherof, whiles the preſt do preſume to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate chriſtes body, nedes muſt they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and graunt by that theyr enterpryſe not ſo godly as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſe that the ſayd body was before the conſecration, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nothyng holy at al, elſe not ſo holy, which graunt as it is er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ronyouſe and vnbeleueable ſo vngodly and exchuable. In ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe the preſtes preſumed only by theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hallowe chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes body, that theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were not ſo haynouſe a dede, but for aſmoche as therby they con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tend not ſo learnedly as ſtoutly not ſo truly as falſely, Chriſtes body to be forged and made of
<pb facs="tcp:11242:13"/> the choſen bread, &amp; therfore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues therby, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſed bread, it is exceding haynouſe, for ther is no creature ſo worthy puiſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; entier, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd body is, why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thyng could not be true, yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt or any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> elſe dyd or coul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de make the ſame. For the ofte making of any thing as of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes body, is an vndeceyueable proufe of the vnperfytenes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines, &amp; feblenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Ther is no man, be he neuer ſo moch prieſted or byſhopped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make the febleſt baſeſt, &amp; vnper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyteſt creature in thys worlde, moch leſſe chriſtes body the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyteſt &amp; nobleſt creature, ther is no creature, be it neuer ſo imper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte that is ofte made, howe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can chriſtes bodye be oft made, that is the moſt perfyte. Theſe wordes take, eate, in theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:11242:14"/> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtitution of the lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, take, eate thys is my bodye, be no wordes of makinge of the lordes body, but of preſenting &amp; exhibiting the ſame to the recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the ryghte ſupper of the lord. So that it is full open that the prieſte can nether conſecrate Chriſtes body, neyther make it. Howbeit, this is alwaye graunt able, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrateth &amp; maketh, though not chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy &amp; bloud, yet thallotted bread &amp; wyne, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes exhitiue of the ſame. For where as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread &amp; wyne vſed at the lordes ſupper were prophane &amp; vnholy, before the wordes of the inſtitution of the ſayd ſupper were duely repor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vpon them, Nowe after thee due reporte, and vtteraunce of thee ſayde wordes by thee myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the before named bread and wine, they be conſecrate and
<pb facs="tcp:11242:14"/> made of prophane the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes exhibitiues, of Chriſtes body and bloud. Thus alſo mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the fathers by theſe wordes, conſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and making in this ſacramente. Nowe to tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiatyon, or tornekynde, thee next entreatable matter, whyche is no leſſe diſallowable, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueable. How can thys ſtande wyth our fayth that Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy (whoſe creatyon is vnrenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) ſhulde be agayn made of the bread a (vyle creature) throughe thexchaunge of the nature ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of into hys? Howe were it true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bleſſed wyne: &amp; broken bread were bred &amp; wyne, as Paule ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yf theyr natures were throughlye altered into chriſtes body &amp; bloud? Can they be bread &amp; wyne ſtyl, without they reteyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne
<pb facs="tcp:11242:15"/> theyr natures ſtyll: Can they be rightly named bread and wyne wythout theyr own proper ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in reſpect, where of they were ſo named: doo they not ſtyll appere to oure ſenſes, bread &amp; wine, not withſtanding, they ar become y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitiues of Chriſtes body and bloud: who euer ſawe the excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of any ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hys accede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhape? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt tourned marueylouſly water into wyne, it had not only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, but the externall forme alſo, taſt colour &amp; facto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wyne, &amp; no ſemblance of water at al, Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s rodde beyng altered into an ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, had not only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, but alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward faſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame &amp; no ſimilitude of a rod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de at al. The water which moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes chaunged into bloude, as it
<pb facs="tcp:11242:15"/> was i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nature bloud, ſo outward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly it ſemed bloud. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo queſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>onles ſhuld y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread &amp; wyne lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward ſhape wyth theyr inwarde ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, yf they were altered into chriſtes bodye and bloud, By reaſon, wherof ſythe they reteygne ſtyl theyr acciden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, nedes muſt they alſo reteig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne theyr wonted ſubſtance, can ther be any ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyne ſayth, without therin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> due eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; fyt word of god be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>longinge ther vnto, be ioyntlye coupled togethers: No verely, How than? can the outward ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peraunce of bread &amp; wyne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theyr inward ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramentes of chriſtes body, &amp; bloud, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward apperau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of bread &amp; wyne be none eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, but only thexternal ſhewes of the ſame. Eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes be ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce &amp; not accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal ſhewes. Is it
<pb facs="tcp:11242:16"/> not true, that in thee conſacrate bread, ther are wormes both en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendered &amp; foſterd whych could not be, yf ther endured the bread lyke natured, after as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſecracion? For eche wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me is a ſubſtance, and none accy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent, therfore cannot be engende<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red or fedde of an accydente, but of a ſubſtaunce alone, In reſpect wherof, ſythe the wormes brede and fede, not in Chriſtes bodye, but in thee conſecrate bread, we muſt remedyles acknowledge in the ſame bread to contynue thee verye proper ſubſtaunce therof. The bread and wyne be ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of Chriſtes body and bloude ordeyned of him purpoſely to en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtructe oure ſenſes outwardelye, what is wrought inwardly by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd bodye and bloud in the ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le. For theyr vſe is to declare too our outward ſenſes aſſuredly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:16"/> as the receaued bread and wyne noriſhe, ſtrengthen and glad our bodyes, ſo chriſtes body eaten &amp; hys bloud dronken accordyngly do oure ſoules. Howe coulde the bread &amp; wyne ſerue to hys purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, yf they were vtterly diuoided of theyr accoſtumed nature? Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely no maner wyſe. For why? it is the alone ſubſtaunce of bread and wyne, and not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colour taſte facyon of the ſame, that foſtereth and cheryſheth the body. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes (ſayth Auguſtyn) vnleſſe they haue certayne lykelyhode wyth the thynges wherof they be ſygnes, they be no Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes at al. What ſemblance I beſeche you is ther betwyxte the nature<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les bread and wyne, and chriſtes body and bloud? queſtionles no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne at all. For the ſayde body and bloude, and that after papyſſhe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:17"/> doctryne be not preſented &amp; exhi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bited at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cially only. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect wherof nedes muſt we gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eyther the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate bread &amp; wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne be not the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body and bloud, whiche we ought not to do, eyther elſe thee ſayd bread &amp; wyne reteygne ſtyl theyr owne natures, whyche is grantable. I maruel me muche that many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who ſtand in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defence of chriſtes corporal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence at his ſupper, haue in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt meyntenaunce tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, for as me ſemethe, it do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth moch, what hinder &amp; preiudi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, the ſayd preſence of chriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd hys ſupper, by reaſon the broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bread &amp; bleſſed wyne be in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitute purpoſely to reſolue and aſcertayn our ſenſes that we as materially &amp; truly, thoughe not groſſelyer ſenſyblie, but ghoſtly
<pb facs="tcp:11242:17"/> receaue and eate Chriſtes body &amp; drinke his bloud as we do the foreſayd: In conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of yf we take, eate &amp; drinke, but the accidentes of thee foreſayde bread &amp; wine, &amp; not the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaunces of the ſame the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gather<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able it were, chriſtes bodye and bloud be not truely, but fayned<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly preſented &amp; gyuen at hys ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per. For why<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yf the ſigne be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terfayt &amp; fayned, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nedes muſt the thing be in ſemblable ſorte, whyche is betokened thereby a true matter muſt remediles ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo true. In reſpect wherof the broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bread being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſygne geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſayd body, is material &amp; not mattierles, thys thenſuyng ſaying, which gracia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reporteth, &amp; fathereth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyne de <abbr>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrat</abbr> 
               <abbr>diſtint.</abbr> ii, cap. qui manducat, enforceth moche to the dyſproue &amp; dampnation,
<pb facs="tcp:11242:18"/> of tranſubſtanciation, That is ſene, is bread, and the cup wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the eyes alſo make euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, but that that faythe demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to be inſtructed in, is, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread is Chriſtes bodye, and the cuppe hys bloud. Theſe therfore be named ſacramentes, for that in them one thyng is ſe able, and another vnderſtande, that is, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne hath bodelye fourme that is vnderſtand hath ghoſtly fruyt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> What can be more effectually &amp; expreſſelye ſpoken agaynſte tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nekynde, then thys the reherſed Englyſſhed ſentence of Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyne? Fyrſt he auoucheth therin the ſeable matter to be bread, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condelye, for an vndeceaueable argumente and tryall therof he alledgeth the teſtimonye of thee eyes, Thyrdly he ſayth not that is ſeeable is a bodelye fourme,
<pb facs="tcp:11242:18"/> but hathe a corporall fourme, leſte anye man ſhulde here be oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſyoned too adiudge the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier to want in thys element and ſo to remayne nothynge elſe but thee outwarde and accydentall ſhape of breade. For in that he ſaythe that, that is ſeene hathe a corporal fourme, he graunteth in thee elemente twoo thynges to bee remaynynge, thee thynge hadde and thee thynge hauyng, thee outwarde faſſyon whych is ſeable and the ſubiecte and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therof, it is to wytt the bread ſubſtaunce and the excernall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce of the ſame. The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente of Thankeſgeuynge, ſaythe Irenee conſyſtethe vpon twoo matters or ſubſtaunces, thee one earthely, thee other hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenlye, Yf bread ſubſtaunce we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re
<pb facs="tcp:11242:19"/> departed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could not I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renee leyfully call y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one part of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce but an earthlye accidente. The worthy counſayl of Nece wryteth to the diſalowau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſorte thus, Let vs not groſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beholde the bread &amp; wyne pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed &amp; ſet before our eyes, but in faythe conſyder the lambe, yf god in that hys ſacred table ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing our hartes eleuate &amp; vplif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, loe, here the worthy counſel nameth the feble portyon of the ſacrament after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecration bread &amp; wyne, &amp; not the formes of the ſame. Gelaſius in open &amp; expreſſe wordes impugneth the ſayd tranſubſtanciatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyouſe &amp; vncredyble in ſorte as followeth. The ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; bloud of chriſt, which we receaue ar ſureli godly matters therfore through &amp; by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we ar made
<pb facs="tcp:11242:19"/> partakers of the godly nature, &amp; yet do they not ceaſſe to be the ſubſtances of bread &amp; wyne, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> properties of theyr owne natures, wher as Auſtyne ſayth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord doubted not to ſay thys is my body, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he gaue a ſygne of hys body: he meanethe not that chriſtes body is abſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys ſupper, but that the conſecrate bread is not the ſayd body or turned ſubſtancially in to the ſame, &amp; is but the ſigne of chriſtes body, notwythſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge it be named hys body. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding Tertullian, Ambroſe, Ierome, Chriſoſtome, wythe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whyche expreſly in theyr wrytynges the conſecrate bread to repreſent Chriſtes body, &amp; to be a ſigne therof, howbeit in tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe &amp; ſoch other, ſemblable theyr ſpeaches, theyr meanyng is not that the ſayd bread is deuoided
<pb facs="tcp:11242:20"/> of Chriſtes bodely preſence and preſentment, but that the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate bread is but thee ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall ſygne of chriſtes bodye, and not chriſtes body ſelue, thoughe it be termed ſacramentallye the ſayd bodye. Nowe wyll I aſſoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le certayne obiections, and gayn ſayinges facyoned of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> premyſſes. Yf ſay they) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bred, nature were not tornekynded into chriſtes body: why dyd he name it hys bodye? Can it be hys bodye, onles it be exchaunged into it? Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I be you wythout I become your ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce? No verely. No more can thee bread be chriſtes body wythoute the exchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of the matter ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of into the ſayd body, As for the accidentes of thee ſayd bread, it is not requiſite, ne nedefull that they ſhuld be together chaunged
<pb facs="tcp:11242:20"/> wythe theyr ſubſtaunce, becauſe chriſte in thys hys ſayinge, this is my body vſeth the artycle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratyue thys, not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine, but in the newtre gendre, whyche implyeth but the alone matter of the bread, and not acci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dentes of thee ſame therwyth, as the maſculine doeth, Whereby chriſt doeth vs tunderſtand that the bread nature is only altered &amp; not his accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyke maner To this obiection, ſoche is myne anſwere. Chriſt in thys hys ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, this is my body doeth inſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tute the ſacrament of hys bodye and bloud, therfore he ſpeaketh vpon the ſame, ſacramentally it is to wyt, he termeth the ſigne by thee name of thee matter therby ſygnyfyed. He nameth the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate bread hys bodye, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is
<pb facs="tcp:11242:21"/> reſembled and preſented therby baptyſe, is named the founteyn of our agayn byrth, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> renuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of the holy ghoſt, yet is it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our newe byrth, nether thee renuyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holi ghoſt, ne chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſo called for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> therby the ſayd byrth &amp; renuing be not only repreſented but alſo wraughte preſented and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto vs,<note place="margin">Gene, 15</note> Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not in very dede the couenaunt made vnto Abraham, ne altered into it, howbeit, it was ſo turned in conſyderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it dyd bothe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, and preſent the ſame co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenaunt to Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: Chriſtes breathe was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, not that it was the very holy ghoſt, or turned in to him, but in reſpect of the ſayd ghoſt therwyth both reſembled &amp; exhibited ſemblably albeit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate bread is named Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes
<pb facs="tcp:11242:21"/> body, yet is it not the layde body ne chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into the ſame,<note place="margin">mathe, 26 luke, 22</note> but ſo called in conſyderacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therwyth the ſayd body is both ſygnifyed, preſented &amp; exhibited. The cup is termed chriſtes bloud &amp; the newe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: Yet that his ſo callyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll depoſe therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the cup eyther to be chriſtes bloud or his teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: Termed notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſayd bloud &amp; teſtament, for that it is y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal mean wherwyth they be applied &amp; conferred vnto vs, Vpon ſemblable conſyderacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the bread named chriſtes bodye. Wher as it is thought &amp; credited the bread ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce only &amp; not hys accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes alſo to be tornekynded into Chriſtes bodye: By reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he vſeth in this his ſaying this is my body, the article thys in the newtre &amp; not in the maſculi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne gendre: Yf this were formally argued
<pb facs="tcp:11242:22"/> is our bonden duety ſo to do. Yet it is replyed &amp; ſayed. Paule cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the conſecrate bread &amp; wyne, this bred, this wyne. Why ſhuld he ſo terme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? In caſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re not turned into chriſtes bodye the other into hys bloud? Verely the conſideration therof is to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs put a difference therby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twyxte the conſecrate &amp; vnconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon breade &amp; wyne, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the former bread &amp; wyne to be ſacramentes exhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of chriſtes body &amp; bloud, and theſe (I meane the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bread &amp; wyne) to be nothing leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicioned. The laſt argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that is alledged for tornekynd is thys. If chriſtes bodye be in thee bred (as vndoubtedly it is) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is enbreaded &amp; his bloude enwy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, whych was alway taken for a great hereſy, In reſpect wherof tranſubſtantiacion nedes muſte
<pb facs="tcp:11242:22"/> be grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted as ryght true and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueable. To thys I anſwere in ſorte thus. Notwythſtandinge chriſtes body be preſented in thee bred (as queſtionles it is) not pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cely as ther placed ſpaced, &amp; meſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, but ghoſtly: as ther vnplaced vnſpaced &amp; not meaſured: Howe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit, it is not enbreaded nomore then the deytie is recompted, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleſhed for that it is ſubſtancially in vs, Nomore then the ſayd god hede is demed e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breaded, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> it is entierly in eche bred. No morothe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy ghoſte is accompted en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breathed, for that he was preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in chriſtes breathe? Nomore then the ſayd holy ghoſt is adiud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged enbodied or enharted, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is wholly in vs &amp; in oure har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Chriſtes body is adiudged of no man to be accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it is preſented in the ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cidentes of the bread. Why then
<pb facs="tcp:11242:23"/> ſhuld it be adiuged e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breaded for hys preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breade. The one is as reaſonable 'as gatherable, as thother is. Some are fule de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued in the meanynge of theſe wordes thimpanacion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bodye, whyche is not in ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple any preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce indefere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly of the ſayd body in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bred: Nomore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> incarnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or enfleſhing of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes godhead is indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly any preſence therof in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fleſhe &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture: But only ſoch a preſence of chriſtes body in the bread wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth they both ſhuld be vnſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably perſoned &amp; haue al theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicions &amp; properties co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Soch a preſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce is the perſonal preſence of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes Godheade in hys manhode. Soch is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body. In reſpect wherof as chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body is not enperſoned i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding it be enbodied to vs: Semblable though the ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:11242:23"/> body be preſented in y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> bred, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, it is not become one perſon therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whych is properly termed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> impaning or enbreding therof? If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bred &amp; wyne be not exchaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Some wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of me, why y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doctors make ſo oft report vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thaltera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breade &amp; wyne. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this myne anſwere. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion why y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forefathers ſo oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port an exchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to be wrought in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of chriſtes body &amp; bloud is. For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they beleued the choſen bread &amp; wyne to be turned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a prophane to a godly vſe, to become nomore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſpecial bread &amp; wyne, &amp; to be made nowe exhibityues ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes body &amp; bloud, where as befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re theyr hallowing they were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng ſo. And not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they beleued the ſayd bread &amp; wyne to be torne ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes body &amp; bloud Thys is the exchaunge wherof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:24"/> doctours make report, and none other doo they acknowledge here beſyde, Thus I haue argued ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually both conſecration &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſubſtantiacion conſtrued, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholique doctryne to be direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repugnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t agaynſt gods wryt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten truth. Now wyll I trye whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the maſſe ſacrifyce in ſembla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſort empugneth the ſaid truth And for ſo moch as this maſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here both for a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſyn &amp; thankeſgeuinge I wyl diſcuſſe fyrſt whether it be a clenſing &amp; ſatiſfactory ſacrifice. This done the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether it be an ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptable &amp; ſeruiceable thankeſge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing to god or no. Concernyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clenſynge ſacryfyce falſely geuen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> Paule wryteth in ſort as followeth: With one offering hath chriſt made ꝑfyghte for euer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſanctifyed. There is not one word in this paules ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diligently &amp; depely conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:11242:24"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enforceth not moch againſt the before ſpecified ſacrifice. In reſpect wherof I wyll report or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, &amp; wayghe eche word of the ſayd ſaying ſeuerally by it ſelfe. Paul ſayth not wyth a manyfold or renewed but with one offering hath chriſt made perfecte for euer the ſanctefied, In conſyderacion whereof they bee foule deceaued, who auouche Chriſtes ſacrifyce ought to be reuiued &amp; multiplied to the ful pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; contentacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſynne, otherwyſe vnpardona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. And therfore repete the ſayd ſacryfyce day by day to the ſame effect. For why that, that is oft of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered cannot iuſtly be reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted to be offered but ones: By reaſon a repeted &amp; renewed ſacrifice is not merely ſyngle &amp; one, but manifol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de &amp; diuerſe. If chriſt had oft died notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he were the ſelue ſame Chriſt, that doeth ſo oft dye Howbeit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> his often dyeng ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:11242:25"/> not be adiuged one ſingle but ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dry deaths. Though it be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſelfe ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me body y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dieth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond deth, which died through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former deth Yet is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twyſe dyeng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted not one but two dethes (as wytneſſeth Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hys Apo.) E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo:<note place="margin">2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> yf chriſt were oft ſacrificed thoughe he were the ſame &amp; none other chriſt that is ſo offered. Yet were that oft ſacrificying of hym no ſyngle one, but a many folde &amp; multiplied ſacrifyce. In conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion wherof, ſythe by the one ot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feringe of chriſte, oure ſynnes be thoughly pourged (as paule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth): Sythe an often offer is not an ones, but a manifold ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce, though it be ot y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelue ſame matter: Chriſtes bodi nether may ne ought to be agayne ſacrificed either bloudely or vnbloudely to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doynge away of our defaultes Now to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entretable text of paul By one offering hath chriſte, &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:11242:25"/> By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ones offeri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of chriſt. Paul meaneth his paynful &amp; bloude ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice, ones done vpon the croſſe for euer, elſe could not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> his ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice pourge our ſynnes. For noo ſacrifice w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out bloudſhed cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth ſyn. According to this ſayinge of paul w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out bloudſheding ther is no remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſyn to be atteigned By reaſon wherof right oppen it is, they greuouſly erre,<note place="margin">Hebr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 9.</note> who hold opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our faultes ar pardoned through theyr vnſufferable &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bloudy ſacrifici<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of chriſtes bodi otherwyſe vnꝓdonable. With o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne offri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hath chriſt made perfyte &amp;c. Note this paul ſayth note in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑſent tence doth make perfect, as though chriſt now doth ꝑdon our ſyns vnꝑdoned before, but in the preterperfyt te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath made ꝑfyt: Purpoſely to do vs herby to wyt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ar already redemed &amp; cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ones offering of chriſt neuer to be reuyued eyther ſufferablye
<pb facs="tcp:11242:26"/> or vnſufferably bloudely or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloudely to purge our ſynnes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al In conſyderacion wherof our catholiques be in a foule greuou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe errour,<note place="margin">Hebre. 10.</note> for theyr auouching (en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forced queſtionles ſo too ſaye not ſo moche of a good ground as of a good entent) our ſynnes clerely to be clenſed wyth theyr vnſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, &amp; vnbloudye ſacryfyce of chriſt. For where remiſſion of ſyn is, ther is (ſayth Paul) nomore a ſacryfyce for the ſame. By one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering hath chriſt made perfyght foreuer the ſanctified. Note this paule ſayth not, Chriſt hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de perfyght for a tyme, but for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſanctefyed. Certes yf chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte were to be agayne ſacryfyced to the ful contentacion &amp; clenſing of ſynne, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd he not throughe hys once offerynge perfyte for euer, but for a tyme the ſanctefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For why the ſacryfyce that is
<pb facs="tcp:11242:26"/> remediles to be reuiued to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſatiſfaction of ſyn con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth god for the ſame, not for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, but for a tyme. By reaſon wherof oure catholikes are to be blamed, who rather erneſtly then godly wil &amp; contend that chriſtes body ſhuld be agayne ſacryfyced to the ſatiſfaction &amp; purgynge of ſyn, otherwyſe after theyr iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnpardonable. An erroure no leſſe deragotorye to the entier<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tee &amp; fulnes of chriſtes ones ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice then preiudiciall to the mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyners therof. For why to renew the ſayde ſacryfyce is vtterlye to vnperfyt, &amp; diſable it quite, fully to clenſe and do away ſyn. For ſo paul argueth to the Hebrues, the ſacryfyces of the old lawe dyd not remyt ſyn, for that they were day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye repeted, elſe not to be renewed If thys be formallye argued of paul (as out of queſtion it is) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:27"/> it argueth that chriſt is not to be agayn offered leſſe hys fyrſt offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring being entier &amp; ſufficiente to purge ſyn be through the repeti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; reuiuinge therof vnperfyted &amp; diſhabled to the ful conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſyn. (An iſſue vtterly wyth al poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible endeuour too bee exchued.) Wyth one ſacryfyce hath Chriſt made perfit for euer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ar holi made. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paul auoucheth her chriſt through his one ſacrifice to haue made perfyt for euer them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ar ſanctified, He doeth vs herby tunderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaintes ar none otherwyſe redemed &amp; ſaued then through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one offering of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd chriſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly no man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be otherwyſe ſaued. For they be ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ſaued: In reſpect wherof it is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> catholiques not ſo godly as ſtyfly maynteyn, it is to wyt we be redemed throu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:27"/> the agayn ſacrificing of chriſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe vnperdonable. For yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe ſacrifice be a conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacion &amp; ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſyn, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> once ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice of chriſt vtterly to be aban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doned &amp; diſauthorized,<note place="margin">Hebr. viii</note> For why to inſtitute a new ſacrifice of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte is tabrogate and adnul thold. Yea yf chriſt muſt be agayn offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation of ſyn, then muſte he be alſo wofully payned and done to death again. For (as the ſayd paul ſayth ther is no con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting ſacrifice without it beblou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy. In conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof,<note place="margin">Hebre. 9.</note> he ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gueth yf chriſt ſhuld be ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nedes muſt he oft ſuffer ofte dye. Wherfore (moſt ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle reder) ſythe of the aforeſayd it appereth ful ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the maſſe mercy worki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g offredge dyrectly gaynſayeth not only .ii. or .iii, but ſondry ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not doubtful but playn
<pb facs="tcp:11242:28"/> and not only ſcryptures (whyche ſymplie to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary is a ſinne ful greuouſe): but endeuourethe it ſelf alſo to mourdre chriſt, whych is more greuouſe): and not onlye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, but vtterly to adnul &amp; aboliſhe chriſtes moſt preciouſe &amp; entier ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice, done vpon the croſſe (why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che for too doo as it is a defaulte moſt greuouſe, ſo moſt vnſuffera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble): I beſeche the hartely iudge and eſteme the ſayd one ſacrifice accordingly, that is to wyt to be the alone ſacrifice wherwith our ſyns be clenſed and done awaye. And thynke and depoſe vpon the pryuate maſſe ſacryfyce as thou oughteſt to do, namely to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng leſſe then a clenſyng ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce, But here wyll oure catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques ſay they doo nothynge leſſe then vpholde the maſſe offeringe to do awaye ſynne, For that they
<pb facs="tcp:11242:28"/> acknowledge wyth vs (the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauntes) belongethe to Chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone. God be prayſed ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore in oure redubted ſouereigne lorde the Kynges maieſtie, Who by a worthy acte of parlyamente, hath enforced the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the outward acknowledge thereof, otherwyſe ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly maynteyning the contrary But in caſe the foreſayd perſons, meaned that inwardly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart, whych wyth the tongue they out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlye graunt &amp; profeſſe: They wold not defend eche parcell of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe canon to be godly &amp; bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable as they do. For why there it is playnly ſayd, the maſſe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice enforceth effectually to the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demption &amp; ramſoning of the ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les. The very wordes of the ſayd Canon be theſe. Remembre lorde thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp;c. for the whych we offre vnto the, or the which do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre vnto the this ſacrifice of pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:29"/> for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, &amp; to thee ramſon of theyr ſoules. Loe, here it is open, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt ſacrifici<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of chriſte (which is here termed a prayſe ſacrifice) is purpoſely purpoſed &amp; wrought to redeme &amp; ramſon ſoules withal Which thing doth apperteigne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonelye to chriſtes ſufferable and bloudy ſacrifice. Wel not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, this thalleged ſayng out of the canon were not playn &amp; ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient enough to proue the ſayd ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>non teſtabliſhe the maſſe ſacrifice to conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t god: Howbeit ther is an other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>les argueth the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, whych the prieſt alway repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth &amp; prayeth in the pooſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lyſſhe wherof is thys. O holy Trinite performe that thys ſacryfyce whych I vnworthy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue offered vnto theyes of thi maie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtie may be acceptable to the &amp; be alſo through thy mercy propicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, that is to ſay mercy working
<pb facs="tcp:11242:29"/> both to me &amp; al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue ſacrificed it. Loe hear in manifeſt wordes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt ſollicieth god pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſely to obteyn of him, this his ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice to be ꝓpiciatory &amp; to appea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe his wrath. In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of grantable it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pryue maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters acknowlege i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very dede theyr maſſe ſacrifice to be mercy worki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g whyles they conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the canon ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of to be throughely true &amp; godlye, notwithſtanding theyr mouth ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. What an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable mockedge is this aſwel of god as of our ſoueraygne lord y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, to acknowlege w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ſacrifice to be nothing propicia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tory, &amp; yet in the canon (otherwyſe named y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe ſecret) to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it offered to redeme vs wythall, &amp; to praye it myghte be propiciatorye, If we hartely thoughte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god &amp; our prince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe ſacrifice were
<pb facs="tcp:11242:30"/> not propiciatorye: We wold not throughlye mayntene the Maſſe Canon, We wold not ſaye there wyth we offer Chriſtes bodye to oure redemption, We wolde not inſtant God as we do, to enforce our ſacrifycing of chriſte to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe hys mercy. But here it is replyed the foreſayde Canon is miſconſtrued. For it meaneth no thyng leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the maſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice is ſatiſfactory in very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, but in name alone. So ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is a reſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or memory of chriſtes pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piciatorie ſacrifice executed and perfyted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe ones for euer. To thys replial thus I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, In caſe the ſayd ſacrifyce were not to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tory, Why is it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heretofore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cioned Canon auouched, We of fre the ſayd ſacrifice to the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both of our ſoules &amp; others?
<pb facs="tcp:11242:30"/> Why pray we that the ſacryfyce myght be made ſatiſfactorye? If we wold not it ſhuld be taken for ſatiſfactory? Yf it were not to be taken for a ſatiſfactory ſacrifice, and that after the true meanyng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who fathered the Canon: They wold neuer haue ſo wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, as they haue done. Again yf we thought not hartely that it were ſoch a ſacryfyce: We wolde not affyrme, we ſacryfyce it to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deme vs and others withal. We wolde not ne durſte ſollicite god to enforce it propiciatorye: dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dredeful ſaying of chriſt thou ſhalt be iuſtified by thi wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des,<note place="margin">mathe, 13</note> &amp; by thy wordes y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned. Let vs hedely beware leſt chriſt iudge vs by our mouth as he dyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wycked ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For the mouthe vttera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as of godly matters maketh to ſaluation,<note place="margin">mathe. 25 Roma, 10</note> as wytneſſeth Paule: So of vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:11242:31"/> to dampnation. Let vs therfore conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne, as of bonde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duetye we ryght) the therfore ſaying of thee maſſe cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Which, as they plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, &amp; directly withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d gods wryt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten worde, ſo the kinges ſtatutes: leſt we through our allowaunce &amp; prayinge of the ſame incurre &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> iuſt wrath both of god &amp; of our prince. Here I cannot but diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cloſe the vnſufferable ſubtiltie of our catheloques in this purpoſed matter. Therfore good reder, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly reſpecte the ſame to thy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoydance of theyr trayn. They ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing in conſyderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that now le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye they cannot: in reſpecte of the pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of gods wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which to gaynſay were not ſufferable: Ne dare any longer vphold theyr maſſe ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to be mercy workyng. For that it emplieth notable repugnaunce to an acte of parliamente whyche
<pb facs="tcp:11242:31"/> not to obey and approue, as it is vnſyttinge, ſo ryght puniſheble: Conſydering alſo yf theyr Maſſe canon were to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d after hys gramer ſence (as doubtles it is) it muſt remedeles be condemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned &amp; canceled oute of the maſſe boke, as hereſye to god, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyſaunce to the King: Wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> happely myght conſequencly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the vtter decaye and confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the maſſe ſelue, (an iſſue no leſſe perfourmable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſonable &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuable): Haue at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fyed and bla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched the ſayd canon in the heretofore alledged places therof after thys ſorte. To offer the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice of prayſe for the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption of our ſoules meaneth nothing elſe, but toffre the ſayd ſacryfyce for a remembraunce of Chriſtes ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce, ones wroughte vpon thee croſſe to redeme oure ſoules wyth
<pb facs="tcp:11242:32"/> all. To praye that the maſſe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce myghte bee propiciatorye is to praye, it myght be a memorye of the propiciatorie ſacrifyce. Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus what a far fetched meanyng of the foreſayd is thys. Whyche cannot wel be ymagyned moche leſſe gathered of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Yf they who fathered the Canon, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the maſſe ſacryfyce were not offered purpoſelye to redeme vs wythal, but to record the ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tore ſacrifice: Theyr wordes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtly wold rather haue enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt ſacrifice to be a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the ſatiſfactory ſacrifice the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be it it ſelf. Therfor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd fathers ſo did wryte the ſayd Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thei might eaſely be vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded what thei vnderſtode ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by, And ſo wrote it ſo openlye as they poſſible could deuiſe. By re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon wherof ſythe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſayinges of the canon make al togethers for the prieſt ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce
<pb facs="tcp:11242:32"/> to be propiciatory Queſtion les theyr meaning is that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſacrifice appeaſeth goddes yre &amp; indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; clenſeth ſyn. Howe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer ours catholiques now ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Though ſaye our catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques) the before eſpecyfyed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations ſeme targue the maſſe ſacrifice to be ſatiſfactory yet ar they to be conſtrued as wee take them, And neuer were they other wyſe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eyther of vs, eyther el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of others learned &amp; catholique me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Lo the ſhameleſſe vanitie of our catholiques, they do not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lye in myſtakinge the Canon, but in miſreporting the myndes of ſondrye wryters. So that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prouerbe is veryfyed one leaſyng doeth accompanye ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Is not Mayſter doctour ſmyth of Oxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ford a great clerke and moch traded in auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters (as it appereth by hys doy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges)? Yet he in the hundereth
<pb facs="tcp:11242:33"/> and one, and twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tye leaffe of hys boke entituled the defence of the ſayed ſacryfyce of the maſſe wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſacrifice to be pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piciatory in ſort thus. Doeth not this place proue the maſſe to be a ſacrifice propiciatorye, Syth by the offeringe of chriſtes body in ſacrifice at it gods wrath towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; his ſeruauntes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued for theyr ſynnes (wherby the deuyl had ſoch power on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) was pacyfied &amp; appeaſed? Agayn in the next leaffe enſuing thus he wrytethe. Nothyngt can be more euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſpoken for the ſacrifyce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holye maſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is a ſacryfyce prepiciatory curing mans woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des (that is to ſay, hys ſynnes) &amp; that alſo by the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of chriſt commaunding it to be done for a reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of hys death and ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to mayſter
<pb facs="tcp:11242:33"/> Smyth? Wherby it is ryght eui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent that he thought the maſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cryfyce to be proprciatory, and I doubte not vnderſtode the tofore named canon as I do. Cocleus a man hyghely eſtemed amongeſte oure catholiques partly for hys ryght iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſcripture mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters (as they ſuppoſe) partlye for hys learnyng, wryteth in hys for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer reply all to Bullyuger in the ſyxt chapter therof for the pryeſte ſacryfyce to bee propiciatorye in ſorte as foloweth. We after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſtumed maner of ſpeaking in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church name not the ſupper but the maſſe, a ſacryfice not onlye of prayſe and thankeſgeuynge, but of mercy workyng alſo, wherwyth we endeuoure oure ſelues to pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe god inſtaunte hym and appeaſe hym. For wee offers the Maſſe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:34"/> maſſe ſacryfyce not for the alone pourgyng of ſynne,) which thou falſely doeſt charge vs wythall, but for ſondrye other ſkylles al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo and nedes. As it is euydently knowen of the holy Canon. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleus</hi> woordes in Latyne be theſe <hi>Nos autem inxtu couſuetum in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia loquendi modum non caena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſed miſſam dicimus ſacrificium non ſolum laudis &amp; gratiarum actionis, ſed etiam propiciationis. Quo deum laudare inuocare &amp; placare ſatagimꝰ Non enim pro ſola peccatorum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piatione (quod tu falſo imputas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis) ſed pro aliis cauſis &amp; neceſſitati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus permultis Miſſae ſacrificiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus, Quem admodum exſacro Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>none liquido cognoſcitur &amp; ex mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiplici diuerſarum collectarum titu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lo verboru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contextu conſpicitur.</hi> Here it is ryghte manyfeſte and playn that Cocle bothe wel lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; godly iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:34"/> opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our catholiques doeth not only ſay that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maſſe ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is ſatiſfactorye, but appealeth to the Canon therin as anſwere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able ther vnto after hys iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Freer Hofmaſter (who was ſo worthely eſtemed of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques as they alotted hym to be one of the reaſoners agaynſt the proteſtantes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperours laſt dyet kept at Ratyſpone) wryteth in hys boke entyteled the expoſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon of the maſſe prayers &amp; cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in the behalfe of the maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ſatiſfactory ſacrifice in maner folowyng. Now that our ſacryfy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce is named a prayſe ſacryfyce I ſuppoſe it offendeth no man. For oure aduerſaries acknowledge alſo the maſſe, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayers lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſgeui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g therin accoſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med to be made, maye be called a ſacrifice of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſgeuing &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, But that we auouche it to be alſo
<pb facs="tcp:11242:35"/> a propiciatorye ſacrifice thys doo they ſtedfaſtly deny &amp; diſaffyrme. Hol mayſters wordes in Latyn be theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Iam ꝙ ſacrificiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letur ſacrificium laudis nominem o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinor offendit. Nam et aduerſarii fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentur miſſam ꝓpter preces, laudes &amp; gratiarum actiones inibi fieri ſolitas ſacrificium dici poſſe euchariſticium hoc eſt gratiarum actionis et laudis. At quod nos aſſerimus preter cetera etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piciatorium ſacrificium hoc conſtanter negant.</hi> Lo, here hof<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayſter not only in hys own, but in the perſon alſo of thee catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques (otherwyſe termed papiſtes) as ful according wyth hym herin auoucheth contrary to our catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liques the maſſe bothe to be a tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keſgeuing and contentation and pardon for our ſynne. This wrote the ſayd Hofmayſter in his before named Boke for the defence and allowance of thys ſayinge of thee canon
<pb facs="tcp:11242:35"/> 
               <hi>Pro quibus tibi offerimus. etc.</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whych we offer vnto the, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che do offre to the this ſacrifice of prayſe for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues and al theyrs for the ramſon of theyr ſoules etc. Wherby we lerne it is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth only of Hofmaiſter, but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foren catholiques alſo, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the maſſe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice is mercy workinge &amp; that thee wordes alſo of thee maſſe canon, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mporte y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame, ought ſo inſimple to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without any far fetched gloſſe. Whatſoeuer our Engliſhe catholiques for a tyme do hold to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. Wel ſyth it is both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knoleged of our catholikes &amp; gro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely I truſt argued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fredge is not ſatiſfactory or ful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. The next entretable matter is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſacrifice is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g auai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lable ether for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quick or the dead Our catholiques co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it is ꝓfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, but how moche or i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what meſure it lyeth not in the powre of man to lymit: But thys
<pb facs="tcp:11242:36"/> theyr opynyon can not ſtande w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chryſtes ſatyſfatorie ſacryfyce. By reaſon it is a full co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſatiſfactyon for ſynne, &amp; ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe ſacryfyce awaleth nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at al to the clenſyng thereof. For yf it auailed any thynge thereto: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wete it propyciatorte aparte thoughe not entierly: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were chriſtes ſacrifice ſatiſfactore but aparte &amp; not wholy: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe ſacryfice no leſſe ſatyſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore then Chriſtes, For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhuld make partely for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſatyſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynne as thriſtes doth: Whyche is a blaſphemy to thynke moche more to ſpeake: Then were oure catholiques deceyued in diſaffyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynge the maſſe ſacryfyce to bee propiciatorye. But what nede I to argue thee ſayed ſacryfyce to be vnfruteful, The catholiques them ſelues in concluſyon grant
<pb facs="tcp:11242:36"/> the ſame, whyle they auouche the full &amp; entier fruyte &amp; vertu of the preſt maſſe to conſyſt in the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of chriſtes merytes vnto vs, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe vtterly diuoided of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ones merit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe in general for alme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; not the ſacrifice, For in thee ſacrifice ther is nothinge applyed and rendred vnto vs, but to God alone, otherwyſe no ſacrifyce at al It is the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alone, &amp; not the ſacrifice that geueth to vs, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the ryghte definitions of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both? In conſyderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof ſythe the maſſe fruyte conſyſteth, not in the preſt ſacrifice, but in the apply all &amp; gyft of chriſtes body &amp; bloud, not as ſacrifice of the preſt (whych is but a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trefeiture &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſemblaunce of thee true ſacrifice) but as offered of chriſte hym ſelfe vpon the croſſe ones for euer: It muſte nedes argue that the maſſe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:37"/> frute co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in the ſacramet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone &amp; not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice alſo. For why y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> appliall &amp; deliuere of thee frutes of chriſtes death &amp; agayn ryſing to vs, is gods gyfte vnto vs &amp; not ours vnto him. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; not the ſacrifice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is auaileable. For a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is defined to be an holy token, wherby god geueth vs fre pardon of ſyns, A ſacrifice co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry wiſe is defyned to be that wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by we re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der ſomewhat vnto god. In reſpecte wherof oure catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques be moch blame worthi, who yelde to the maſſe ſacryfyce why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is apperteyninge only to the Lordes ſupper, I meane the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all &amp; render of the benefygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of chriſt is deth &amp; reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whych dyde as it is a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded proufe of falſhode ſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnauai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leablenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe, as otherwiſe vnfrutful, Though (wilſom ſay) the maſſe ſacrifice applyeth not,
<pb facs="tcp:11242:37"/> ne rendreth to vs chriſtes mery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Howbeit wythoute that they cannot poſſibly be preſented and deliuered vnto vs. And ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſacrifice muſt no remedy be auay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leable. That is not ſo. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd merites begyuen vs both in bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme &amp; abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea &amp; in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to wythout the preſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce as ſhal here after be decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, And ſo the ſayde ſacryfice in thys reſpert is fruytles. Yet doo our catholiques replye, the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd ſacryfyce ſaye they, though it maketh nothing to the applial of chriſtes merites to vs warde: Howbeit in that it is a tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it muſt nedes be auaileable In this replial fyrſt this is deny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the preſt ſacrifying of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes body &amp; bloud is a tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merely &amp; nakedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected as nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g but an offredg nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked thereby, &amp; ſo no tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kgeui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g:
<pb facs="tcp:11242:38"/> In dede the prayers incident ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to be a thankeſgeuinge. But beit the ſayd ſacrifice were a thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuinge. Yet it ſhall not orderlye here vpon enſue that it were an ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptable &amp; auaileable tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſgeui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge For ther be two ſortes therof, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one good &amp; proffytable, thee other nought &amp; vnfrutefull? And yf the preſt ſacryfyce be a tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſgeuing it muſt nedes be both vngodlye &amp; vnfrutefull, &amp; ſo of the badſort of thanke render, By reaſon it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute beſyde gods wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; ſo contrarie to the ſame, in that it is a putting therto. For yf it were fonded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayd word it ſhuld by al lykelyhod be gron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon chriſtes wordes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge his ſupper. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is not And ſo it is a forged worſhip &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kerendre, For chriſt at his ſupper neyther offered hym ſelf ne inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:11242:38"/> others to ſacrifice him to his father. Orderly examine eche word of the inſtitution of hys ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per &amp; ye ſhal wel apperceaue thys to be ful certayn. Chriſt at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſupper tuke bred,<note place="margin">mathe. 26 Luke, 22</note> But that is not to ſacryfyce hym ſelue. Els he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyced hym ſelue to hys father ſo oft, as he dyd eate. He gaue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, but that is not to offere hym ſelue, Els he ſacryfyed hym ſelue to hys father, what tyme he encre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed fyue barelye loofes &amp; fed ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyth fyue thouſand men. He bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it and gaue it to his diſciples. But that is not to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre it to god, whych is behoueful in eche ſacry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce. His diſciples toke &amp; eate the bread &amp; his body, ſo do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lea me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in lyke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, Yet they offre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not The which is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you, herby he meaneth not to be here ſacrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Els ſhulde he offer hym ſelue oft, and not ones, Els wolde not
<pb facs="tcp:11242:39"/> our preſtes ouerhipped thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des in theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were enioned to do this in his reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſo they dyd: What then? So doo all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes &amp; the faythful lealtye per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Yet offer they hym not. As ther is not one word tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this former part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords ſupper, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enforceth for the prieſte ſacrifice: Euen ſo is ther none in thys latter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maketh for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, is reducible &amp; appliau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the latter portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſayde ſupper. Thus it appereth playn chriſt nether of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered him ſelue in hys ſupper ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded others to offer hym in the ſame to hys father. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect wherof paul ſpoke the ſelue ſame wordes vnto the vnpreſted Corinthians<note place="margin">1. Cori: 11.</note> whych Chriſt repor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to hys diſciples. And bad the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo perfourme all thoſe thinges
<pb facs="tcp:11242:39"/> whyche Chriſt demaunded to be perfourmed of his diſciples, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thing be wold neuer haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnpreſted Corin. mought not acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed &amp; put in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al matters concerning the lordes ſupper. Thus it is playn the maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ſacrifice is not grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon Goddes wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word, &amp; ſo nether acceptable or ſeruiceable to God ne fruteful to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For why, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo worſhippeth god wythout his ſpecial word for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth him wythout fayth. By rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon true fayth iſſueth onlye from gods wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word as wytneſſeth S. Paul. Fayth cometh by heari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hearinge by gods word.<note place="margin">Roma. 10</note> And who ſo worſhippeth god without fayth, ſynneth. For as Paul ſaith whatſoeuer thing is not of fayth,<note place="margin">Roma. 14</note> is ſyn. So that hereby it is full ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayd ſacrifice is ſynful &amp; conſequently not to be freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted or vſed. Our catholiques in that
<pb facs="tcp:11242:40"/> that they acknowlege theyr prieſt ſacrifice not to be mercy workyng ſuppoſe it ſo take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may wel ſtande both with goddes word &amp; chriſtes honour. But in ſo demeng they be foule deceyued. For why to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt to offer chriſt as it is an enterpry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe toto bolde and preſumptuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: ſo vnſufferable &amp; blaſphemouſe. For thys is the ſtate &amp; condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of leyfull ſacrifyces before god, that they ſacryfyced be not merelye of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, but in reſpect of the offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rers godlynes regarded and hys ſynfulnes dyſlyked of God. The ſacryfyces of Abel and Cain, not wythſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng they were not moch what vnlyke in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues:<note place="margin">Gene. iiii,</note> howbe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>it they were dyuerſly reſpected of god in conſyderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ory<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes betwixt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offerers. For thone god regarded for Abels ſake, the other he hated and abhorred for Cain ſake. The lorde loked vnto
<pb facs="tcp:11242:40"/> Abel (ſayth moyſes) and to hys of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fering. But to Cain and hys offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ringe he loked not. Marke thys, Fyrſte he loked vpon Abell ere he reſpected hys offeringe. Fyrſte he dyſlyked Cain or he diſlyked hys ſacryfyce, Whereby we do vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that the offering is lyked or diſlyked of god in reſpect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rer. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> here vpon it grondelye arguethe that the offerer is bothe worthyer &amp; better eſtemed of God then hys offering. For that, that god regardeth merely for it ſelue is better &amp; more eſtemed of hym, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that whiche he regardeth but in reſpect of another. In conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration wherof yf chriſt were to be ſacrificed of thee prieſt, then were the prieſt bothe worthyer &amp; better accepted before god the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt him ſelue, as it is gatherable of the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſayde. By reaſon wherof thee prieſt ſacryfyce as it moſt hyghly
<pb facs="tcp:11242:41"/> empayrethe chriſtes honoure &amp; maieſtie ſo vncomperablely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth god the father &amp; ſo moſte exchueable. Wolde you further know why y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt ſacrifice is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitting &amp; diſalowable? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlye note the ſequeles, &amp; after ſayinges, Who ſo be autoriſed &amp; appoynted to ſacrifice Chriſt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy muſt be preſtes after the order ether of Aaron or Melchiſedech, But our offerers ought not to be preſted after Aarons order. For that his preſthode is quyte repea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led &amp; done away. Syth the prieſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hode ſayth Paul is tranſlated of neceſſite muſt the law be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alſo,<note place="margin">Hebre, 7</note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remediles muſt the foreſayde ſacryfycers be prieſted after Melchifedech order, els are thei vnpreſted. But thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be preſtes as melchiſedech was: By reſon who ſo is a preſte after hys order is an euerlaſtynge prieſte accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to this ſaying of dauid<note place="margin">Pſal: 14,</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:41"/> Thou art an euerlaſting preſt af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order of Melchiſedech, but we be al immortal &amp; but for a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, therfore not eternall &amp; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly none euerlaſtinge preſtes, Whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it formally argueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our vſurped preſtes vſurpe &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the authorite to ſacrifice Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes body, whych is grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne to anye ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> els. By reaſon wherof they be blame wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr vſurpatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſoch autorytee.<note place="margin">Hebre. 5</note> Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth Paul take honoure to him ſelue but he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called of god as was Aaron To ꝓcede further in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſproufe of the preſt ſacrifice, Howe can it poſſible be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our preſtes could ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifi chriſtes bodi &amp; bſoud? With out theyr due ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde body &amp; bloud nether ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſented ne ſacrifyced, as the preſtes them ſelues acknoledge as moſt certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrified bred &amp; wine nether be ne ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of chriſtes
<pb facs="tcp:11242:42"/> body &amp; bloud: By reaſon they be otherwyſe vſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt ſelue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned thee ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to be. Can the baptiſme water be iuſtly reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wher it is tranſpoſed to other vſages the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is prepared for of chriſt by hys word &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, namely to be gaiſed vpon, too ſprynkle &amp; waſhe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al, to chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> belles to waſhe our clothes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all? No truely. Can the circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on or of pare which the Iewes and turkes now vſe, be rightly demed a ſacramente? No verely. Certes nomore can the ſacrificed bread &amp; wyne be iuſtly accompted ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes body &amp; bloud. But heere oure Catholiques replye ſayinge the wordes of conſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be reported vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bread &amp; wyne ere they be ſacryfyced, In conſyde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration wherof, nedes muſt they be ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Thys ther replial is nothinge formall ne forceable &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:42"/> by theyr own doctryne. Be it that alayma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reported the conſecration wordes on the bread &amp; wyne or the preſt vttered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not purpoſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> making of chriſtes body &amp; bloud. The ſayd bread &amp; wyne were after our preſtes doctrine nothing leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geuing ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboue named body &amp; bloud, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding the report of the conſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wordes ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So that it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth wythe catholique doctryne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſymple the bare report &amp; naked vtttrance of the conſecration wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des enforce not the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. So that the foreſayd replial is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g effectual, being neyther true ne ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholique? Now to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> before mencio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned ſacrificed bred agayn, I put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe, ther were ſoch adueuout prieſt who were ſo deuoutly diſpoſed as he wolde eate none other breade &amp; drinke none other drinke at mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les but ſacramentally conſecrate
<pb facs="tcp:11242:43"/> bred &amp; wyne &amp; wold in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereof for eche his dyner and ſupper purpoſely report daye by day at hys maſſe, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecration wordes ouer hys bread &amp; wyne y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he wold vſe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde meales: I ſuppoſe noman be he neuer ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiq<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; old faſhioned wyldepoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayd bred &amp; wyne to be geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of chriſtes body &amp; blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the report of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wordes ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, And verely the conſecration hereof is the dyrecte &amp; oppe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abuſe agaynſt the ryght inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vſage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramentes of thee ſayde bodye and bloud: Nomore be the ſacry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyced bred &amp; wyne ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of chriſtes body &amp; bloud, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reherſal of the conſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wordes ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: For why chriſte inſtituted at his ſupper his body not to be ſacrificed but ete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpecte wherof he ſaythe not take
<pb facs="tcp:11242:43"/> ſacrifice, this is my bodi: but take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eate, thys eate my body. Ther be thre matters ryght nedefull &amp; be houeful to the natural beynge of a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, The due element the due word y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſpecial commaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god directed therto. Wher any of the aforeſayd want, there can be no ſacrament. By reaſon wherof the ſacrificed bread &amp; wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they be the due eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes conſecrate wyth due wordes. In conſyderation ther wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth gods ſpecial commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo to auto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſe vs &amp; able vs to ſacrifice the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; eate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So that they be but pure eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; no ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Therfore chriſtes body &amp; bloud ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not poſſibly be ſacrify<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced in &amp; by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whereby it appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt ſacrificing is of nothing leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy &amp; bloud. Thus (good reder) I haue
<pb facs="tcp:11242:44"/> argued (I ſuppoſe forceably) the prieſt ſacrifice to be nether propi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciatore ne auaileable, nether god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ne approueable but ſinful and vnſufferable. Therfore I beſech y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vtterly renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it &amp; deteſt it en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bracing &amp; vſing in the ſtede ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of the moſt holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion. But happely thou art loothe ſo to do tyl I haue ſoyled the reaſens fet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched out of ſcriptures whych co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourably ſeme to ratefy the ſayd ſacryfyce, By reaſon whereof I wyl addreſſe me to the ful anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as it is argued chriſt in reſpecte he is priſted after Melchiſedech ordre offred him ſelue bodely vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the fourme of bread &amp; wyne, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Melchiſedech offered bread &amp; wine. This reaſon holdeth not becauſe it is falſe that Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dech ſacrificed bred &amp; wyne. For Moſes ſayth not Melchiſedech
<pb facs="tcp:11242:44"/> offered but brought forth bread and wyne. To bring forth is not to offer, He ſayth not he brought forth bread &amp; wyne for a ſacrifice but wythout any me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice at al. He ſaith not he brough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te forth the ſayd bread &amp; wyne to god, but to Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it is right gatherable of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hiſtorie to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do ſacrifice were an ymage ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice, &amp; therfore Melchiſedech ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crificed not bread &amp; wyne. Here it is obiected yf Moyſes meaned not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> melchiſedech offered bread and wyne: Why adioned he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly thereto this? he beynge the preſt of the moſt hygheſt god bleſſed hym? Mary not becauſe he ſacrificed the bred &amp; wyne but for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he bleſſed Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doynge vs hereby to wete, as Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech declared hym ſelue to bee a kinge in employing vpon Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham bred &amp; wyne: So in bleſſing
<pb facs="tcp:11242:45"/> hym to be a preſt. For as the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying of bread and wyne, was a kingly function, ſo the bleſſing a prieſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffyce. In conſyderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof the foreſayd Moſes thus wryteth. And Melcheledech thee Kynge of Salem brought forth breade and wyne,<note place="margin">Gene. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iii</note> and he was a prieſte of the mooſt hygheſt God and bleſſed hym. The meanynge wherof is thys as me ſemeth) be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe Melchyſedech was a kyng he played the kynge he employed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hyghe chere, bicauſe he was a prieſt alſo, he played the prieſte he bleſſed hym. In that he was a King he chered Abraham, in that he was a prieſte he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hym. But here ſome wyl ſaye Abraham was alreadye greatly enriched wyth kyngly ſpoyles &amp; hadde no nede of Melchiſedechs chere, therfore by al lykelyhod he profered hym not the bread and
<pb facs="tcp:11242:45"/> wyne. To thys I anſwere, not wythſtandynge Abraham neded not Melchyſedech cheringe, yet he chered hym in fuile proufe of hys hoſpytalyte and humanytie toward both hym and his. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hus both Chriſoſtome and Ioſephus thynke. But be it Melch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſedech offered breade and wyne, and in ſo doyinge fygured chriſt Shall it folowe there vpon, that Chriſt offered hym ſelue bodelye infour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of breade and wyne? Noo verelye. Was not Aaron a fygu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of Chriſte, dyd he not fygure and reſemble hym ſelue in ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycyinge of a gote? Yeas certayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. Yet noo man wyll or oughte to gather, bycauſe Aaron who was a fygurer of chriſt ſacrificed a gote, Therfore chriſt offered hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelue corporally in or vnder thee
<pb facs="tcp:11242:46"/> ſhape and kynd of agote. If the before mencioned doying of mel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chiſedech were applied to chriſte after this ſort folowing I could not but acknowledge the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation therof both ſufferable and godly, As melchiſedech the king of Salem profered bread &amp; wine to Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; hys ſodiers, not for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſacrifice, but to eat to their relief, &amp; bleſſed the ſayde Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in him al his poſterite: Righte ſo chriſt our kynge, the kynge of ſpiritual peace &amp; rightuouſnes, preſenteth at his ſupper to al vs his communers bothe bread and wyne (ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes exhibitiues of hys body &amp; bloud) not to be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but thone to beeate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; thother to be dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to oure comfort, and bleſſeth vs al, &amp; in vs al oure of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring. The next alledged reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe ſacrifice is this dedu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced oute .i. &amp; .iii of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝓphet Mala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chie,
<pb facs="tcp:11242:46"/> I haue no wyl to you ſayth the Lord of hoſtes &amp; I wyl not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue of your hande a ſacrifyce. For from the ryſing of the ſonne vnto the gowing down myname is great emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the people. Lo her (ſay our catholiques), y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet propheſieth of the vtter refuſall and repeale of the Iewyſhe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce &amp; of the ſucceſſion choſe and acceptau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a new, whych is to be vnderſtande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the maſſe alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. This ther vnderſtandinge is nothing anſwereable to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes meaning. For why he ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth only of ſoch ſacrifice which is offered in al places of al men and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the morninge to nighte. The maſſe ſacrifice is not ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced in eche place, but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church alone, not from the morninge to night, but from the morninge to noonetyde, not of eche man indif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferently, but of the prieſte alone.
<pb facs="tcp:11242:47"/> The alledged reaſon out of thee eyght &amp; twelue of Daniel enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth nothing to the preſt ſacrifice For daniel as it appereth playne in the nynthe chapter entreateth of the aboliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Iewyſhe dayly ſacrifice, whych is diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynued for certeyn yeres through the tyran Antiochus. This ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice was offered twyſe on the day in the mornyng &amp; at nyght. The Maſſe ſacrifice is ſacrificed but ones on the day, &amp; that in the mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng, thother was offered but in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Hiercuſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyced in eche churche. Yea the mooſt learned catholiques ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not endure thee foreſayde Prophecye ſhulde be ſo take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it concerneth thee quyte aboliſhement of theyr Maſſe ſacryfyce. For that they be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue that as Chriſtes churche is euerlaſtable ſo theyr ſayde ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice alwayes endureable. It is
<pb facs="tcp:11242:47"/> expreſſely wrytten in, xiii. of thee Acres of the Apoſtles (ſay our ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholiques) that they ſacrificed to thee Lorde. Therfore by al ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleaunce they ſacrificed his body and bloud. What a miſfaſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned argumentation is this? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Apoſtles ſacryfyced to the Lord, ergo they ſacryfyced hys body &amp; bloud. Could they ſacryfyce no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the ſayd body &amp; bloud? Mought they not preache, pray, gather almouſe for the nedy and mynyſtre the Lordes ſupper? Be they not al ſeuerably ſeruiceable and acceptable ſacrifyces? Bee not alſo the ful executours of the ſame iuſtly named ſacryfyers? Yeas verely, Then it is nothing enſuable, becauſe thee Apoſtles ſacrificed, they ſacrificed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bodye and bloude. And Luke ſaythe not they ſacryfyced
<pb facs="tcp:11242:48"/> chriſtes body &amp; bloud, but in ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple they ſacrificed. Therfor this ſaying of luke they ſacrificed im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porteth neceſſarelye no ſacrifyce of chriſtes body &amp; bloud, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beforeſayde. That here Eraſmus nameth ſacrificinge, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> old tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlator termeth miniſtring Chriſoſtome takethe it for prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge, ſo dothe Eraſmus alſo. The greke word ſaye y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Pariſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s betokeneth to execute &amp; miniſter a publique office, &amp; it is here ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to preache gods goſpel, Thus the Pariliaus in theyr annotaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Thus it is euident the before alledged argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation is both wrong fra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med &amp; diſproued both of chriſtoſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me Eraſmus &amp; Pariſians y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hed maynteyners of the maſſe ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. Another reaſon that the catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liques alledge for thee maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of theyr ſacrifice is thys
<pb facs="tcp:11242:48"/> The thyng fygured muſt agree wythe hys fygure. Chriſte was fygured by the paſcal la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the ſayd lambe was firſt offered ere it was eaten:<note place="margin">Exodi. xii</note> Euen ſo chriſte (the true lambe) was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ere it was eaten, at his maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy. To this I anſwere after this ſorte. It is ryght certayne that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter figured &amp; the figure both do &amp; muſt accorde in ſome poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, otherwyſe ther can be neyther fygure ne thing fygured: In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof the paſcal la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be (for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſygneth chriſt) it muſte &amp; dothe reſemble hym in ſomwhat &amp; ſo it doth. For as the paſcal la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be was ſlayne &amp; offered, ſo was chriſt. As the paſcall la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be (ſlayne and offered) was a meane where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by the Iſraelites were deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr ſlauery of Pharao, So chriſt mourdered broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; offered was the meane wherwyth we be
<pb facs="tcp:11242:49"/> fredomed frome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thraldome of our ſpyrtual Pharao y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll. As y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſcal lambe was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered but eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo: ſo Chriſt was both eaten &amp; ſacryfyced &amp;c. But y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinge fygured ſhuld be throughly ordred as hys fygure in all pointes, it is neyther nede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful ne poſſyble Els ſhuld Chriſt haue bene offered but of others alone &amp; not of hym ſelfe alſo. In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſcall lambe was ſo Els ſhuld he haue bene roſted ere he were eaten, bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lambe was not eaten rawe but roſted. Els his bones ſhulde haue bene bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayd lam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bes were, Els his bloud ſhuld ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue bene ſpringled in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes was, Els he ſhuld not haue bene eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whole &amp; vnbro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn ſufferably but by pecemele and ſufferably as the lambe was Wherfore ryght as Chriſt is fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured
<pb facs="tcp:11242:49"/> trueli by the paſcal lambe notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding his foreſayd diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therwyth: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe chriſt is fyrſt eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficed yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is none hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce why the ſayd chriſt ſhulde be fygured by the paſcal la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, Now to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is adiudged to enforce for the maſſe ſacrifice. Ye cannot drinke of the lordes cup &amp; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils to? Ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be partakers of the lordes table &amp; the deuils alſo Here S. Paul co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pareth the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the lordes ſupper with the communion of the meates of fred to the deuyls,<note place="margin">i. Cori. 10</note> whych thinge certaynly he wold neuer haue do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne oneles he demed chriſtes body and bloud fyrſte to be ſacryficed ere thone is eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thother dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the meates dedicate to deuyls be. For els y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon were nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſemblable ne formal. To thys is myne anſwere: Paules
<pb facs="tcp:11242:50"/> ſayd compariſon betwixt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd body and bloud, and the meates and drinkes conſecrate to deuils conſiſteth only in mutual receipt and comunyng of them, and noo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing at al in the ſacrificing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Therfore he mencyonethe only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partaking and not theyr offredge alſo: I meruel me moch what our catholiques meane to auouche thee before mencyoned comparyſon not to be formall w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oute it implied the offredge alſo both of the ſayd meates and drin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. May not two thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges be iuſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly compared togethers and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> but in one ſymple matter? Doo they not know that eche compariſon halteth and in ſome matters diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth? Yf they wyl haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tofore named co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon ſo throu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghly anſwerable &amp; ſembleable in all condicions: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is to be ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gued after thys poſycyon, and
<pb facs="tcp:11242:50"/> decre that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy is eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hys bloud dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and that accordinglye, yet they ſtaine and embrue vs in conſyderatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ymage meat and drinke, eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo do. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do they alway dyſpleaſe god, for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meates and drinkes offered to ydols ſo do, The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be groſſely ſenſybly and ſufferably eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and dronken for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the meates and drinkes of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to Idols be after that ſort both eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Al thees in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes be no leſſe gatherable of the foreſayd compariſon then that Chriſtes bodye and bloude ought to be ſacryfyced. In conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ydol meate and drin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke be offred. Is it not in expreſſe wordes in Paul .v. to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hebrues (ſaye our catholiques) that eche Byſhop or prieſt take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the nombre of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ordeined for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thoſe thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do appertei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gn
<pb facs="tcp:11242:51"/> to god that he ſhuld offre gyftes &amp; ſacrifices for ſynne? whereby it is full open that oure prieſtes do offere a ſacrifyce for oure ſynne? What can that bee but Chriſtes body &amp; bloud? Fayn wold our ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholiques haue theyr maſſe ſacry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce to be authoryſed &amp; founded vpon gods wrytten worde, but it wolde not be. I beſeche the what enforceth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alledged text of Paul to the maynteyning of preſtes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice? Verely nothing at al. For why it talketh only of the Aaroni cal ordre of prieſthode, as it doth well appere by this the after ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge of Paul, let no man take vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym honoure (he meaneth the foreſayde prieſtehode) wythoute he bee called of God there too as Aaron was, and compareth thee offyce of thee ſayde prieſtehode wyth Chryſtes as it is ryghte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uydente
<pb facs="tcp:11242:51"/> by thys thee nexte after ſpeache whych begynneth in ſort thus. Euen ſo lykewyſe Chryſte etc. And he ſpeaking but of the le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiticall prieſthode oughte in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe too be vnderſtande of oure maſſe preſthode, according to the generall rule. Eche man ſayinge muſt be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after the entended &amp; entreated matter. Well though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſayd allegatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Paul were to be conſtrued of oure Chriſtian prieſthode &amp; of our chriſtian p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. Howbeit, it oughte ſo too be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it implieth nomore one chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, nomore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritual the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding ſome be eccleſiaſtical mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) whyche other be not) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this ſaying of peter, ye be a kingly preſthod, But beyt ther be certayn allotted &amp; choſen to a ſpecial ſort of preſthode,<note place="margin">i. Pet. ii</note> whyche the remnaunte of Chriſtians, be not allotted to, Iet ſhuld the here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tofore
<pb facs="tcp:11242:52"/> alledged ſcripture argue nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. By reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it entrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth of ſoch preſtes who ar won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to offre not one gyft, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; diuers, not one ſacrifice, but ſondre, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ful conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſyn, oure made prieſtes offre but one gyfte, yf they offer that but one ſacryfyce and not dyuers, and that not to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction and purging of ſynne but for a thankeſgeuing, as our Catholiques the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelue now at the laſt acknowledge. Yet thee ſayde Catholiques replye for ther ſaid ſacrifice in ſort thus? Chriſt ſayd to his apoſtels (as Luke .xxii. ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth hereof report), Thys do for my reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce, which thys his ſaying autoryſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſacrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce chriſtis body and bloud as he him ſelue had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> done at his ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per. This theyr replicationis no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing effectual or true, Was not
<pb facs="tcp:11242:52"/> S. Paul an apoſtle not of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt but hygheſt ſort? howbeit he dyd not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſayd ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of chriſt after that ſort. For he ſpoke the very ſelue ſame to y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> vnpreſted Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">i. Cori. xi.</note> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> not of his owne hede, but by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the lord. I haue (ſayth he) receyued of the lord, Which I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue delyuered you, wherby it doth wel appeare that it is not onelye Paules, but the lordes alſo &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſequently al his apoſtles mynde, that thys hys ſayinge do thys in my reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce, is ſpoken aſwel to the vnpreſted as to the preſted chriſtians. By reaſon whereof yf thone be through the ſayd ſpeche autoryſed to ſacryfyce chriſt is bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, the other is in lyke maner. If the one be not, the other ſorte can not be? In reſpect wherof our Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholiques acknowledging the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſted not to be autoriſed throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:53"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſpeach auctoryſed to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice chriſtes bodi, thother is in ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er. If thone be not thother ſorte cane not bee. In recſpecte whereof oure Catholyques ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgynge thee vnpreyſted not to bee auctoryſed thoroughe the aboue alledged ſcrypture to offre Chriſtes bodye and bloud: muſte no remedye graunte thee preyſtede not to be lycenced by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſcripture to ſacrifice y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Thys partecle thys in thys chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes ſayenge thys dooe in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce as it is a ꝓnou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latyue ſo demonſtratyue, therfor reporteth declareth &amp; reſpecteth hys antecedent, whyche was not to ſacryfyce hys body wherof he forſpoke neuer word ne did anye thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame but onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kful receipt &amp; eating of his body &amp; drynkyng of hys bloude, ther purpoſeli me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cioned. Which
<pb facs="tcp:11242:53"/> ymplie no maner ſacrificing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame at al, This is grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſwell of the catholiques as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proteſtantes as a trueth moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doubted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laye &amp; vnprieſted ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receaueth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munyon vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely, what tyme ſoeuer he take it not recording therwyth the precy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous death of the lorde. But howe could the ſayd ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receaue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion vnworthely for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceypte therof wythout myndeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of chriſtes paſſion &amp; death, yf for to ſo take it, were not a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able defaulte? For why the vnwor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thenes herein iſſueth from ſynne alone. But how were it ſynne, yf it were not directly repugnaunte agaynſt Goddes oppen commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demente? For there is noo ſynne whych is not a breach therof. But what commaundemente is there for the laye men to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes deathe at theyr receypte of the
<pb facs="tcp:11242:54"/> of his ſupper, yf thys do in my re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce be not it, yf it touche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not? Certaynly none. By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherof nedes muſt we reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gniſe &amp; acknowledge eyther that the vnpreſted ꝑſons receyue not vnworthely the ſayd ſacramente when they take it in forgetfulnes and ſyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of chriſtes paſſion, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is nothing grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table, eyther els that this ſaying of chriſt, this do in my reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth, &amp; chargeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd perſons aſwel, as the preſtes, whych is ryght cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyn. In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof, this do in my reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce purporteth not to ſacrifice chriſt in hys reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce but to recorde &amp; declare ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly hys death (as Paul ſayth) who exponeth the ſayd ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 11.</note> in thys wyſe. As oft as ye eate thys bread &amp; drinke thys cup, ye ſhall ſhow the death of the lorde tyl he come. Yet are not oure Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques
<pb facs="tcp:11242:54"/> contented but further they procede in theyr replial. We ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue an aulter wherof they may not eate whych ſerue thee tabernacle: Here ſaye they. Paule meanethe thus. They who kepe the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyes of Moyſes lawe haue none authoritie to eat of chriſtes bread hys very body co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated &amp; offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in ſacryfyce on the aulter whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che we chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men haue ſet vp in our te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples. If Paul had not mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned this he wold haue made noo me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of an aulter whych is ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de for ſacrifice to be offered ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to God. See (good reder) how foule deceyued be the herfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re named perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Is it not ryght euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that Paul ſpeaketh of an eateable aultar? We haue an aul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tare (ſaythe he) wherof they maye not eate,<note place="margin">He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp; not of thee maſſe ſtone aulter whych is not eatable. If y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſayd aultare were to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a
<pb facs="tcp:11242:55"/> ſtone aultar Then were they who truſted in the ceremoniall lawe in better caſe then we Chriſtians be For that they moughte not, wee muſt eat y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd aulter, The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld Chriſtes body &amp; bloud thone ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue bene eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thother dronking in Paules tyme at the aultare &amp; not at the table,<note place="margin">1. Cor: 10,</note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold Paul haue termed the eatynge place of thee lordes ſupper not the lords table, but the lordes aultar, Then wold not the Apoſtles haue gone from houſe to houſe to myniſter the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munyon,<note place="margin">Art: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for that there was none aultare. Then do oure mynyſtres treſpace who exhibite &amp; mynyſtre the ſayd communion to the dyeng men at home, were wantethe an aultare. Chriſte is onlye the eata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aultare heretofore eſpecifyed, whom bothe we muſt and do eate vnto lyfe euerlaſtynge otherwyſe ſpyrytuallye dead for euer, as we
<pb facs="tcp:11242:55"/> maye learne the ſame in Ihon: vt The which chriſt is named an aul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tar, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him alone we laye &amp; powre our ſpiritual ſacrifices na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely our prayers &amp; broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hartes, otherwiſe not acceptable to god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father according to this ſaying of Peter.<note place="margin">1 Petr: 2</note> Offer vp ſpiritual ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces acceptable to god for Ieſu chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte ſake.<note place="margin">Hebre. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> By chriſt ſayth Paule we offer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice of prayſe alway to god, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wete the fruytes of tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe lippes which confeſſe his name Thys is the laſte argumentacion of them that be deduced &amp; fetched out of the ſcripture which ſemeth any thing forceable for the preſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice. As touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thys place of Mathew. v. When thou offereſt a gyft at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aultar. etc, Notwythſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cioneth expreſli both an aultar &amp; an offredge: Howbeit for ſo moch as it was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vttered whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ceremoniall lawe of Moyſes ſtode in hys wounted effecte and
<pb facs="tcp:11242:56"/> and force whych co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both to be vſed, and ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obliged &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to obey the ſayd law: For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was not ful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute &amp; ratified: It enforceth no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng at al for like offring &amp; aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare to be freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; vſed emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs chriſtians. By reaſon the here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tofore named law is through the ordinaunce &amp; eſtablyſhment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vtterly abandoned &amp; repeled.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> In that ſayth Paul he ſaythe a new Teſtamente he hath abrogate the old. And as touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thys ſayinge of Paule.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> And they which wayte at the aultar ar par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>takers of the aultar, it importeth nothing at al in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> behalfe of maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſacrifice, wherof ther is no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion made. It is but the fourmer parte of a ſymylitude fetched out of the ceremonial law of Moyſes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As in moyſes
<pb facs="tcp:11242:56"/> law, whoſo ſerued the aultare (as thee Leuytes dyd) lyued thereby: Ryght ſo (now in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) who ſo preacheth the goſpell ſhal haue hys lyuinge through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachment therof. For Paule in his the alledged texte &amp; others in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cidente hereto, endeuoureth hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelue to argue a lyuelyhode to be deiu &amp; payable to the goſpel, prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers of theyr auditours for ther euangelical preacheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (dere reder) wel the entier and full ſayinge of Paule, &amp; you ſhal eaſely perceaue he meaneth thus Do ye not (ſayth he) vnderſtande how that they whych miniſter in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple haue theyr fyndynge of the temple, And they which wayt at the aultar ar partakers of the aultar? Euen ſo, alſo (note the ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fourme two ſymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes) dyd the lord ordeyn that they whyche preache the goſpell,
<pb facs="tcp:11242:57"/> ſhuld lyue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel. Yf the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſymylitude we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſo to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhuld meane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> now ther be certen miniſters who ſhuld ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aultare, it is to wete ſhuld maſſe it, then the goſpel prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers ſhuld not maſſe it at al. For that by Paules doctryne to ſerue the aultare &amp; to preache be ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye and ſeuerable offices and mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſteryes, Which thyng accordeth not with our catholique doctrine, which teacheth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the goſpell prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers muſt maſſe it alſo. But wat meane I to be ſo moche in the ſoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng of theſe two laſt recited ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, whych yf they had bene any thynge effectual for the proufe of the prieſte ſacryfyce, as the before alledged ſeme, Mayſter doctour Smythe wold haue pleaſed them wyth in hys boke made for the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence of thee ſayde ſacryfyce, as he hathe doone thee remnaunte, and
<pb facs="tcp:11242:57"/> not in the margente therof. Thus haue I at full both declared and argued that Chriſtes bodye and bloud ought not to be ſacryfyced of the Maſſers in theyr maſſe, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to clenſe our ſynne, eyther els to thanke and ſerue god wythall, and that the reaſons which the ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholiques deduce out of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture to the mayntenaunce therof enforce nothing for the ſame. But ſaye oure catholyques the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente and holye Doctours as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyne Chriſoſtome and others ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſely auouche thee Lordes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and bloud to be offered of the miniſters, whych thyng they wold neuer haue affyrmed oneles they were offered ſo in verye dede, and that accordynge too Gods worde In dede it is fulle certayne that the ſayd Doctours auouche both thee LORDES bodye and
<pb facs="tcp:11242:58"/> and hys bloude to bee ſacrificed but not after oure Catholiques meaninge. For why they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the ſacryfyce of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body &amp; bloud done by the mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſter only the reſembleance and memorye of the true &amp; bloudy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce of the ſayd body &amp; bloude which is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion &amp; not any real &amp; true ſacrifice of the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ecuted by the prieſt as the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques miſtake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We ofte vſe to ſaye (ſayth Auſten to bonifaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eaſtrr approcheth nyghe that to morow or the next daye is the lordes paſſion &amp; yet it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares ſythe he ſuffered and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was neuer but ones: And vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonday, we ſaye this daye he dyd agayn ryſe, howbeit, it is many yeres ſence he roſe. Now is there no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo foliſſhe to reproue vs as lyers, for ſo ſaying, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe we name thoſe dayes after the ſimilitude of thoſe, in whych the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:58"/> matters were done, ſo that is called the ſame daye which is not the very ſame daye but by courſe of tyme lyke it. And it is ſayde to be done thee ſame daye throughe meane of the celebration of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament whych is not done the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me daye, but longe tofore. Was not chriſt ones ſacrificed in hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelue? &amp; yet in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed for the people not onelye eche eſter holy day, but eche day? And he lieth not who beinge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded anſwereth he is offered For yf the ſacramentes haue not ſome ſembleaunce of the matters wherof they be ſacramentes, they were noo ſacramentes at all. Of this ſembleau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce oft they take the names of the thynges by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyfyed. Lo there it dothe full wel appere that by Auſteynes mynde the ſacramente of chriſtes body &amp; bloud is ſo named thee ſacryfyce of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both as eſterday is named
<pb facs="tcp:11242:59"/> the day of the lordes reſurrection &amp; good frydaye his paſſyon daye, But the ſayd dayes benot termed fsr y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord in very dede agayne ryſeth in thone &amp; reſuffreth in tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, but by reaſon his paſſyon in thone hys reſurrectyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thother is repreſented &amp; ſignifyed. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes body &amp; bloud not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they be ſacrificed verely i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, but in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideracion theyr ſacrifice is bothe recorded &amp; reſembled in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde communion or ſacramente. The celebrating of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion ſaythe Ekius in the tenthe chap. of hys fourmer boke of the maſſe ſacrifice (dedicate to the kynge of Pole) for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is an ymage reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice) may be named alway a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. As Auſteyn ſayth to Simpli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cius, Images ar wonte to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> names of thoſe thynges
<pb facs="tcp:11242:59"/> wherof they be ymages, Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we vteu &amp; beholde a paynted table or walle we ſaye thys is Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero, thys is Saluſt, thys Ceſar, Here we ſe both by Auſteyne and Ekius iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the communyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is named a ſacryfyce of Chriſtes body and bloud for that it is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleaunce &amp; ymage of the ſame ſacryfyced. By reaſon whereof nedes it muſt argue, as the yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of a thynge is not thee thynge ſelue: as a paynted man is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dede, as Ceſars ymage is not Ceſar ne Saluſtis Saluſt ſelue: So thee Maſſe or Communyon beynge but an ymage and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ſacryfyce of chriſtes body and bloud is not thee verye true ſacrifice of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bothe, And as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion is named the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſayd body &amp; bloud, in conſyderatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayd ſacrifice is ther in both recorded &amp; reſembled
<pb facs="tcp:11242:60"/> Ryght ſo the miniſtring &amp; ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ebra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion is vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyke reſpect termed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifyinge of chriſtes bodye &amp; bloude. Thus meaned our forefathers by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cryfice &amp; ſacrificing of the ſayde body and bloud. Now to the laſt matter incident to the maſſe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice whych is the worſhippe &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans of whole chriſte bothe man and god, in &amp; vnder the fourmes of bread and wyne. A dede no leſſe vnſytting &amp; repugnaunt too the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelical truth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be. The pryue maſſe worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pers holde opynyon that Chriſte ought of congrue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red &amp; prayed after the conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as beyng in the preſtes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des for that he is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there bothe god and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſo ther no leſſe honoura<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble &amp; prayable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, But thys theyr argumentacion is no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:11242:60"/> dialectical or formal. For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the preſence of Chriſt in a place importeth not the honour &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng of him in the ſayd place. Is not god the father eſſenciallye in eche creature? Yet he is reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced &amp; ſollicited, but as reſident in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; not in hys creatures. Is not the holy ghoſt in eche faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſon? Howbeit no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippeth him as preſent in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, but as in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Chriſt is pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent in eche religiouſe aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled faythfully in his name, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, &amp; pray vnto hym as reſyant in the religiouſe aſſemble but in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen alone. Is he not as god eche wher &amp; conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly at the maſſe? Howbeit no man adiudgeth hym there to be worſhipped &amp; called v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, yf hys body were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, The experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wherof is playn in that part of the maſſe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:61"/> that forgoeth conſecration. Why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld hys bodely preſence en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force vs to honour &amp; ſollicite him in the ſayd maſſe? For his body is not honourable ne prayable mere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly of it ſelue but in reſpect of hys godhedde perſonally alyed &amp; cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pled therwyth. Chriſt both god &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his father &amp; the holy gooſt is preſent at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> baptiſme of fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full infantes where they become enbodied &amp; incorporate therto, it is to wete where they eate his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; drinke his bloude as reallye as we do at his ſupper: Howbeit no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſhippeth eyther hys bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy as preſent at baptiſme ther no leſſe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at his ſupper, ey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther els his godhed, ether for his own or for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſens of his ſaid bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, Why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld ether his body be honoured as preſent in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe after the conſecration or els thee preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof cauſe vs to honour
<pb facs="tcp:11242:61"/> his godhed in the ſame, ther other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe vnhonourable? As in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde teſtament (as we learne in the .vi. of Daniel) the Godlye fathers in theyr exileme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dering in farre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom dyd in all theyr prayers made vnto god dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte bothe theyr hartes and theyr eyes toward Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; wher ſo euer they cam, dyd ſollicite god as inhabitant in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: ryght ſo we being as pelgrimes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this world, exiled as were from heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Hie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and natyue countrie where god dwelleth muſt honour &amp; pray vnto hym alway as reſya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; not els wher It is wrytten in the canon of thee moſt worthy counſayl of Nyce in ſort as foloweth. Let vs not groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely beholde the breade and cuppe propoſed &amp; ſet before our eyes but in faythe, conſydere thee lambe of
<pb facs="tcp:11242:62"/> of god in that hys ſacred table w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our myndes eleuate and vplifted Here we ſe the moſt worthy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl inhibiteth &amp; diſwade the vs from gayſing &amp; tootinge vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bread and wine, aduertiſing vs in faith to reſpect chriſt in his ſupper, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing our myndes erected vp into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, In caſe the ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl had eſtemed it ſitting &amp; leyful to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp the bread (as the moſt parte of the lealtye, I had almoſt ſayde of the clergie to doth, an ydolytre deteſtable), or chriſt in the breade (as in maner all chriſtiando<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth a lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table caſe) it wold not haue forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs to to ote vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bred &amp; aduertiſed vs to vplift our har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Doth not the preſt him ſelue at his maſſe ſaye a little before eleuation or ſacringe? We haue our hartes aboue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord? How eyther ought or can chriſt be reuerenced &amp; oncalled as preſent
<pb facs="tcp:11242:62"/> in the ſacringe yf we, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſer &amp; quere doo ſinge, haue &amp; oughte to haue (throughe the decre of the church) our hartes &amp; eyes two (for where oure hartes be there muſte our eyes be faſtened alſo) aboue erected vp into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the lorde For yf he were to be conſidered &amp; honoured in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhuld haue our hartes beneth &amp; not abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue downward &amp; not vpward to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhuld at that inſtante worſhyp hym in the preſtes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des &amp; not in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Chriſt preſcribing vs an exacte trade &amp; perfyt forme to praye wythall, enioyneth vs in the ſame to inſtant &amp; on call God the father in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher he him ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue is reſydent on hys ryghthande (as Paule ſayth) &amp; not els where notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he be eche where, Our father ſayth chriſt whych is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſayth not whych arte eche where. In reſpect wherof
<pb facs="tcp:11242:63"/> bothe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne be to be worſhipped &amp; praied to i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one &amp; not els wher, For to praye otherwiſe (ſaieth Cipria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte tought vs is not only an igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce but a vice alſo,<note place="margin">mathe. 15</note> ſyth he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth why do ye infri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; break god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des iniunction purpoſely to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſh your tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Chriſoſtome i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys expoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er writeth as foloweth, where as Chriſt ſaieth God is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth not by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſo ſaie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clud &amp; heme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> draweth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who makethe his praier to hym, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth &amp; faſtneth him i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his homely vpon the ſayde prayer he wryteth after thys forte Se where ye cal vpon the father, verely in heauen vpon conſidera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion whereof we crye at thee vicu of thee ſacryfyce, oure hartes abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue, where oure confeſſyon is boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, lette oure hartes bee repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
<pb facs="tcp:11242:63"/> Hytherto Chriſoſtome who in theſe hys ſayinges that Chriſt is not to be honoured &amp; prayed to in the earth &amp; ſo not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſinge place (apart therof) but in heauen Further ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther be made to god at any tyme an effectual prayer with oute an vplyftinge of oure har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, vnto hym? No verelye. Why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pray we to chriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring? Wher ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be none vplifti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge but a downliftinge of our hartes. In ſo moche as the places where chriſtes ſupper and the maſſe, bee celebrate (as al other places vnder heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) be beneth &amp; not aboue. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyn in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> behalfe of the premiſſes writeth, ſuper lectione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelii co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite or tibi pater etc, in ſorte thus, Faythfull perfetly know where &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſayd, let vs re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord our god. For noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes to the lord, who hath not his hart vpward to the lorde. Note, this he ſayth not who hath
<pb facs="tcp:11242:64"/> his hart downward but vpward, beneth but aboue, dyrected but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, in the earth but in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the lorde. Dyd not chriſt ſelue al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye pray to hys father his eyes erected vp into heauen, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth in Ihon. xvii? Why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do we not directe our prayers to the Trinite, not as beynge here there or els wher, but in heauen alone? But here it is obiected y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manye dyd worſhyp &amp; inſtante Chriſt as beyng ſeably conuerſant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>monge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">mathe. 8</note> namely Thomas Peter &amp; the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rouſe perſonne &amp; therefore wee may in lyke maner honoure hym and on call hym in the maſſe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munion. To this I anſwere, albe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>it chriſt was worſhypful &amp; praye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as beyng emonge vs, whyle h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was ſenſiblye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſaunt with vs: By reſon he as god &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was the ſeable emong vs &amp; vnaſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: How beit for ſo moch as he is now become both vnuiſible
<pb facs="tcp:11242:64"/> emong vs, &amp; reſyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, on hys fathers ryghtha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, he is both honourable &amp; prayable but i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone &amp; not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth, &amp; conſecrate bred &amp; wine. For whi to worſhip hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vnder or before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd bread &amp; wyne: is to worſhyp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame bread &amp; wyne. As to worſhip god in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or before an ymage is to reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence thee ymage ſelue, whych is an vnſufferable ydolatree &amp; alſo diſalowed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges maieſties proceding.<note place="margin">Ionn: 4 Colloſ: 3.</note> Chriſt is truth ſpirite &amp; the body, as Paule ſayth, In re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpect wherof he is not to be honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red moche leſſe called vpon, in or vnder ſhadowes &amp; carnal thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges ſoch as the bread, wyne, pyxe &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther earthlye thynges be. But in ſpirite &amp; veritie wythoute fygure ſhadowe or any other carnal thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge as he hym ſelue ſayth in Ihon iiii. The Catholyques the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues graunte it ydolatre to worſhippe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt body vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread, yf ther
<pb facs="tcp:11242:65"/> were remayning the ſubſtance of the ſayd bread, why than worſhyp we the fore ſayde bodye vnder the bread ſythe as I haue heretofore argued the bread ſubſtance is not altered. Wel thoughe it were, yet why ſhuld it not be ydolatre to ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour chriſtes body vnder the acci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dental and outwarde fourmes of bread? For in thys maner as well the accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of bread be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as in thother thee ſubſtaunce therof. Now doth he ſhow (as the father and the holy ghoſt do) his glory &amp; maieſtie but in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding he be eche whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. In reſpecte wherof he is to bee adored &amp; ſollicited in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone and not els where. For honoure &amp; prayer importe the preſence of his glorye and maieſtye where they be exhibited to him And as a king re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth to be honoured as a king where he dyffynneleth hys perſon
<pb facs="tcp:11242:65"/> age and maieſtye royall. Ryghte ſo Chriſte dyſſymuling hys Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty renoume &amp; godly perſonage here emong vs refuſeth to be reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>renced &amp; called vpon as hee is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs. He is as meate recea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued &amp; eaten &amp; as drinke taken and dronken at hys ſupper: and thee maſſe alſo (yf he be ther receaued at al). By reaſon wherof he is to be honoured and oncalled nether in the one ne in the other, bycauſe meat and drinke be nether honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red ne inſtanted. Thys it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worſhyp &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to chriſt at the maſſe, hys ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or els where, heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exempted is diſſonante to the ſacred ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re worthy counſayll auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours good reaſon &amp; the nature &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of true prayer and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendable. But here wolſome ſaye God is too be honoured and prayed to in all places and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſequentlye in the prieſtes handes
<pb facs="tcp:11242:66"/> at the eleuation or els where. To this I anſwere notwithſtanding we ought to honour and ſollicite god eche where, howbeit our pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers &amp; worſhippes made vnto him here or ther muſt tende &amp; be direc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to him as inhabitant &amp; reſiant in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; not as here ther or els wher in the earth. Why then wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſome ſay doth Auſteyne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worthy clerke wryte to the contrarye? He ſayth noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eateth chriſtes fleſſhe onles he fyrſt worſhyppeth it and ſynneth it, he worſhip it not? Wel though Auſteyne ſaythe Chriſtes muſt be worſhipped, yet he gayn ſayth not me, becauſe he ſayth not noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eateth chriſtes fleſhe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out he worſhip it as in his ſupper or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe in or vnder the bread, but in ſymple without any ſoch lyke glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe worſhippeth it. Yea though he were to be vnderſtand to talke of ſoch worſhip whych implieth the
<pb facs="tcp:11242:66"/> honour and inſtaunce of the ſayd fleſſhe. By reaſon he maketh noo clere me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion wher the ſame ſhuld be worſhypped, he is to be taken to entreate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhipping of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cioned fleſhe in ſoch pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce wherein it is not doubted but certenly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is worſhipped, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and not of any earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly place. But Auguſtyn meaneth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of chriſtes fleſhe no ſoch worſhippe as, honouring prayinge crowchinge or knelinge therunto, but only the worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent and holſome receypte &amp; ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of the ſayd fleſhe. For the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour due and requiſite to the ſaid fleſhe or ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therof, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as chriſte inſtituted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee receaued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wete wyth pure fyeth clenſed conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wyth vnfayned repentaunce charitie &amp; thankeſgeuing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ful deſyre and purpoſe to be fedde wyth chriſtes
<pb facs="tcp:11242:67"/> fleſhe to be therbye mortefyed too ſyn &amp; ſanctified, to be enbodyed to chriſt &amp; not to crouch before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bred to his fleſhe or to worſhyp inuoca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; ſollicite him as preſente in or vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bred. The ryght vſage of gods word &amp; his ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes is re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted theyr due honour as theyr abuſion diſhonoure. The worde Baptiſme &amp; abſolution throughe meane of true &amp; obedient fayth, &amp; clenſed conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be condignely &amp; accordingly receyued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ether crouching or kneling eyther wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippinge or prayinge to God as preſent in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. So thee lordes ſupper is worthely &amp; ryghtely ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate &amp; receyued wyth oute thee foreſayd crouche worſhyp &amp; inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. Thus haue I at full ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt part of the maſſe, Now to the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d whych co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receypt of the lordes ſupper which wether it bee in very dede as it is named
<pb facs="tcp:11242:67"/> it happely may be wel doubted v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon. Yea as me ſeameth it is not in dede. For ſyth at the preuy maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ther is none to ſuppli y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roumth &amp; office of chriſt in miniſtring the ſupper it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be the lordes but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſtes ſupper. For w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out chriſte or his miniſter his ſupper cannot be made ne diſtribute. Wythoute chriſtes wordes touchinge the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of hys ſupper be duelye reported at the recepte of the bred &amp; wyne ther cannot be his ſupper. How then can the maſſe ſupper be the lordes? ſyth ther wanteth hys mynyſter, who ſhulde reporte the ſayd wordes? Yf the pryeſt preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to pronounce them they be the prieſtes and not chriſtes, for that they be the wordes not of the gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer whyche is Chriſte, but of thee taker whyche cannot be he. Yf it were thee Lordes ſupper that the Pryeſte takethe at hys Maſſe he
<pb facs="tcp:11242:68"/> he ſhuld receyue it of the lord and not of hym ſelue. But how can he poſſibly receyue it of the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd, ſith ther is none preſent to exhibit the prieſt it in chriſt name? But ſome wol ſaye the prieſt may ſupplye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon, both of the inſtitutour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hybitour &amp; receyuer of thee maſſe ſupper, therfore it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes. Yf thys y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is obiected were true, then mought one baptyſme hym ſelue, aſſoyle hym ſelue, confyrme hym ſelue, marrye hym ſelue, annoynt hym ſelue, whych no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo catholique wol graunt, By reaſon as thei be thought al to he inſtitute of chriſt ſo they muſt all be executed in hys name &amp; autori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te Which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther is no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to ſupply his r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he. For the receyuer of thee premiſſes cannot poſſibly play both the part of the geuer and of the taker. By reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:68"/> they be twoo ſeueral perſons. To this the catholiques alſo condiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de as moſte certayn. Therfore as in the heretofore eſpecified ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies (ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truly but al ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiqueli termed ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes) one man alone cannot receyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for want of a ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d perſon who ſhuld mynyſter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him in the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des name &amp; autorite notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hathe vſed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receypte of the ſame eche worde re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quyſit &amp; behoueable therto: Right ſo the preſt endeuouryng hym ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue to receyue the lordes ſupper ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not receyue it without chriſtes mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſter an othere perſon ebeſyde him ſelue, notwithſtanding he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth all thee wordes appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge to the ryght &amp; ful inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſayd ſupper. For as the abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cioned ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes the recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers reporte of the wordes belon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecration of anye of
<pb facs="tcp:11242:69"/> the ſayd ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes enforceth not the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes? Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, his repor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of the baptiſme wordes ouer him ſelue, in waſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him ſelue, or hys reherſal of the abſolution wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelue, maketh nether baptiſme ne abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the preſt beynge but the receyuer that is to ſay, he who wold receaue the lordes ſupper, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not through hys own report of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes appertey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſayd ſupper, inſtitute or cauſe the ſame Ther is no ſacrament which hath not for his ordinaunce &amp; eſſenſiall beyng bothe hys deputed element word &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Wher is ther any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yea or ſuffera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to take or inſtitute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords ſupper alone? Certes not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. Can ther be inſtituted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſupper wythout the due reherſall of the wordes concerninge the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me? Can the ſayde wordes be iuſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:11242:69"/> eſtemed chriſtes not conſtrued as he meaned them? Noo verelye, Therfore lette the maſſer reporte them in hys pryuate Maſſe ſo oft as him lyſte, they be not the lordes wordes. For that take ye, eate ye drynke ye, implye both a commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demente and a ſeconde perſon to the receypt of the Lordes bodye &amp; bloude, and to the conſecration of the ſacramente of the ſame, Why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che bothe wante in thee Pryeſtes ſupper, and ſo it is not the lordes. Wherfore as it is falſly ſo preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuouſly &amp; blaſphemouſly termed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords ſupper, But let it be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the maſſer takethe in hys maſſe, yet it is there haynouſlye abuſed, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is celebrate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to hys commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement &amp; otherwyſe then he inſtituted it.<note place="margin">luke. xxii</note> He bad vs ſeuer the conſecrate breade charitablye emong vs &amp; not eche of vs to reſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue it to hym ſelue, and to eate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charytablye
<pb facs="tcp:11242:70"/> al alone, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſt dothe.<note place="margin">Math. 26</note> He bad vs take &amp; eate hys bodye &amp; not to worſhip it &amp; vplyft it as the preſt doth.<note place="margin">1. Cor: 10,</note> He bad vs at the celebratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; receypt of his ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, receaue &amp; eat hys body in his reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfully to ſhowe his death emong the congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych the prieſt pretermyttethe &amp; not to ſacrifice his body &amp; bloude as the preſt dothe:<note place="margin">Math. 26</note> He bad vs ſaye not only take eate this is my bodi but alſo which is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you (a clauſe moſt fruyteful &amp; nedefull) Which the preſt as vayne &amp; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fluouſe ouerhyppethe. He bad vs take &amp; eate hys body for oure ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues alone &amp; not for others alſo in that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth vs to eate it, for noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can effectualli eate it for another, But the preſt doth not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye eate it for hym ſelue, but for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo, both quyck and dead. Which as it is vnpoſſible for him
<pb facs="tcp:11242:70"/> to do effectuallye ſo to attempt is a ſuperſtition. Can another mans eating releife myn hunger? Can hys drinkinge releaſe my thyrſte? Can another man be baptyſed aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyled, prieſted, maryed, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmed or anoynted for me? How then can the preſtes receypt &amp; celebratinge of thee communion be myne or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleable to me? Chriſoſtome vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .xv. chap. of the fyrſt to the Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rinthians wryteth to the maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the premiſſes in ſort as followeth. As one man cannot be chriſtened for an other ſpeciallye beyng dead, ſo noman can receyue the body &amp; bloud of chriſt for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther namely beynge dead. Hereto agreeth Antididagma. but be it it be ſo that the prieſt may receaue &amp; eate the lordes ſupper for others, whether they be quycke or deade. Yet for as moch as he cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſibly beleue for another (the iuſte
<pb facs="tcp:11242:71"/> man ſaith Paule ſhal lyue by his owne fayeth (it muſte no remedy be that he both taketh and eateth the Lord is ſupper to thee damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon of them,<note place="margin">Roma. i.</note> whatſoeuer they bee good or bad deade or quycke for whom he taketh and eateth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. By raſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he taketh &amp; eateth the ſayd ſupper for theym vnwor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thelye for wante of hys beleuyng for theyme, whyche is merelye nedefull to the holſome and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye receypte and vſage of thee before mencyoned ſupper. Well thoughe it were ſo that the preyſt bothe coulde at the Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for others, and beleue for theym alſo: Howbeyt in ſo much the ſayde pryſte vſyth in hys ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſſyng the ſayd ſupper, otherwyſe then Chryſte hym ſelue inſtytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it (as is heretofore declared) nedes muſte hee receyue it bothe to hys own dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; others,
<pb facs="tcp:11242:71"/> Bicauſe (as S, Ambroſe wryteth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leauenth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte to thee Corynthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) who ſo vſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſupper otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hym ſelue ordened, receiueth it vnwor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thely &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to his da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as paul ſaith.<note place="margin">1. Cori: 11.</note> Thus it is pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> priuate maſſe ſupper is to be diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynued &amp; ſurceſed as blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemouſe to God &amp; annoyous to the practycioners therof, and the deuocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and holynes, that is ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed to be in the vſage thereof, is mere ydolatrye and ſuperſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and ſo both dampnable an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> excheuable. Wherefore they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deme it both reaſonable and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, that the maſſer mought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it alone, whan others refuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctlye to maſſe wyth hym <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> no man oughte to be a ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and hinderaunce of an othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocyon, be no leſſe deceyued the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thee Iewes, who adiuged theyre
<pb facs="tcp:11242:72"/> conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pning of the eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelical doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne &amp; perſecuting of chriſt &amp; his diſciples both a ſufferable &amp; ſerui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceable ſeruice too God, in conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration it was done of deuotyon. Now to prayer the thyrde part of the ſolytarye maſſe, whyche is for ſoundrye conſyderatyons blame worthy. Fyrſt for that therin thoſe ſainctes bee on called as aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers &amp; ayders who be not here pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſently conuerſant emonge vs but ar fare ſoundred &amp; diſtanted from vs in place namelye in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For though we mought praye vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſainctes as beyng preſentlye and conuerſaunt wyth vs as wee do one to another aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers, howbeit for aſmoch they be farre placed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs (they in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth) we ought not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For why that were to attribute and render to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour dewe and incidente to God
<pb facs="tcp:11242:72"/> alone, it is to weete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of our hartes and the hearinge of the farre abſent, In caſe I beyng at Cambredge dyd deſyre eyther you, eyther any mans the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beynge not preſent wyth me, but eyther at yorke or London to praye for me, (whom otherwyſe preſent with me I mought both wel and wyſely): wold not eche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> depoſe that my deſyre bothe vaynelye and vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretely made of me? Bycauſe noo man beyng at that preſent, eyther at yorke or London, what tyme I praye to hym in Cambredge, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heareth or vnderſtandethe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my prayer? Yeas trulye, How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can our prayers be fruyteful and effectual which be directed to the heauen ſainctes who be farrer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanted or ſound red from vs then eyther London or yorke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bredge? But the heauen ſainctes w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l ſome ſaye beynge conuerſant
<pb facs="tcp:11242:73"/> or preſent wyth God eſpye in hym as in a glaſſe, al the ſecretes &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of our hartes, &amp; ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly perceaue what we praye for &amp; to whom, This ſophiſtical cauil or obiection is nothing anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to Goddes worde wherin it is expreſly wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſorte as folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.<note place="margin">ii. para. vi</note> Thou alone knoweſt the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the ſonnes of menne Howe coulde thys be veryfyed and iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed that god alone vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth mens hartes, yf the heauen ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes knowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo? Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth Eſaye .lxiii. knoweth vs not, Iſra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell knoweth vs not, So maye we ſaye, Paule knoweth vs not, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knoweth vs not. For why they were aſmoch pryueledged &amp; regar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded as Peter &amp; Paul. It is wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in thee .ix. of thee boke named preacher, that the dead knowe the nothing any more, vpon the why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che text Hierome ſayth thus. The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is noo knowledge after death,
<pb facs="tcp:11242:73"/> ne any ſenſe after the diſſolutyon of thys lyfe. Wherfore as it is an vngodly ſo an vntrue ſayinge the heauen ſainctes knoweth our har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes not wythſtandynge theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation wyth God. It was no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tably inhibited in the counſayl of Carthage that any ſaincte ſhulde be called vpon at thee aulter, that the prieſt ſhuld vtter thys or lyke prayer. S. Paule or Peter praye for me, Why then contrarye both to the ſcripture and the ſayd god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly counſayl do we inſtant ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciouſli the heauen ſainctes at our maſſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g? But ynough hereof. The ſeconde conſyderation, why maſſe prayer is to bee diſcommended is by reaſon therein, it is prayed for the dead, not ſo moche too declare therby our charitie towarde them in wiſhinge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaued (which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ware no leſſe ſufferable then charitable) as throughe our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers too redeme them oute of pur-
<pb facs="tcp:11242:74"/> of purgatory or at leſt to enleſſen theyr paynes in the ſame. Whych for to thynke wel done as it is an vntollerable erroure ſo for to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte is a ſynneful ſuperſtition. For who ſo dothe departe oute of this world, dieth eyther in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde or without him, If he die without hym the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> incontinent remedyles he is condempned. For wythout chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte ther is no mercy to be achyued or hadde,<note place="margin">ii. Corin.</note> al promiſſes ſayth Paul be in chriſt, yea and amen. But yf he die in the lord he is both bleſſed and enfranchiſed from al trauayl as S. Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wryteth in, xiiii. of his reuelation. In that Iohan auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the departed in thee lorde to be bleſſed, he doth vs to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d they be not payned in purgatorye els were they curſed &amp; not bleſſed, In that he pronouncethe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al labour, he doth vs to were they be no more moleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:11242:74"/> or torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted eyther in purgato<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye or els were, els ſhuld thei endu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re in labour, For to bee payned in purgatorye is a greuous trauayl Agayne whoſo dieth in the Lorde dyeth in fayth, whoſo dyeth in fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the, eſcapeth both deth and iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſo conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly purgatory al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo, whych is a payneful iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t after our catholique doctrine.<note place="margin">Iohan, v,</note> Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely, verely I ſay vnto you ſaythe chriſt, He that heareth my wordes and beleueth on hym that hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me, hath euerlaſting lyfe and ſhal not come into iudgemente but is ſcaped from death to lyfe, As con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge the other dead ſort as it dyeth wythout chriſt ſo wythoute fayth, therfore it is euerlaſtinglye and ſo not pardonably in purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, but vnpardonably placed in hel. Wher vpon it formally argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth ther is no purgatorye. Thee dead ſaythe Salomon in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ix. of
<pb facs="tcp:11242:75"/> of his boke entitled, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preacher, ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue nomore a reward. Whych hys ſaying were not true, yf they mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght be through our prayers ſacry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fices or otherwiſe deliuered out of purgatore. For theyr deliuery we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a great reward. Yf any ſhulde come to purgatore it is very like &amp; colourable y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the thefe which was ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt, ſhuld haue ben for a ſeaſon placed &amp; payned therein. bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſoch a ſynful liuer as he was tyl his dieng houre, but he inconti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t after hys hence departure, we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt to paradiſe. In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof it is right certeyn that purgatore is but an ymagyned &amp; fayned place, by reaſon wherof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiers &amp; ſacrifices inſtitute to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leaſe &amp; redeme ſolles out of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me (otherwiſe called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrd place wherein they be payned) be bothe vayn &amp; ſtuperſtitious. The place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Machabees which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques alledge to the mayntenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, mac, 12</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:75"/> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd place is not aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tical or receiued for ſcripture, as Hierome Gregory Ruffinus record. The ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nones whiche the catholiques fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles, the cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the laſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl of Leedes &amp; Aphricane regeſtred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bible bokes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cion made of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Machabees at al, which argueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bokes of Machabees were vncanoniſed It is wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heretofore alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Machabees y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iudas cauſed both ſacrifice &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yer to bemade to purge &amp; do away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyn of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> murdered Iewes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>al, &amp; is in the ſayd boke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſo doyng which is an vndecea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueable argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaid boke is not aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tical or canonical. For the leuiticall ſacrifices dyd not do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſyn before god. It is vnpoſſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſayth Paule to the Hebrues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bloud of oxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; gottes ſhuld ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke away ſinnes.<note place="margin">Hebre. x</note> Agayn ther be no ſacrifices or prayers commanded
<pb facs="tcp:11242:76"/> of god in the behalfe of the dead. Therfore the before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cioned bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke is nothinge leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> canonical In conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it approueth mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters added to gods word co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to his expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">Deut, 20</note> Here iucide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly by the way we may lerne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſyth god in the old law (the tyme of vnperfection) inioyned neyther ſacryfyce ne prayer for the dead, it is not bys mynde that now in the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (the tyme of perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) he being alſo now moch more mercyfull the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before chriſtes incar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation ther ſhuld be made eyther ſacryfyce or prayer for the dead to redeme &amp; releaſe them wyth al (as otherwyſe vnredemed &amp; payned) Forther yf the foreſayd boke were throughly wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the enbrethin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of the holy ghoſt (otherwiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>canoniſed as Peter ſaith) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this enſuing clauſe ſhuld not haue ben interplaced in thende therof,<note place="margin">ii, Petr, i,</note> 
               <note place="margin">ii, mac, 15</note> And
<pb facs="tcp:11242:76"/> if wel, &amp; as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenable for a ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, I wyſhe the ſame, yf not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely, I muſt be pardoned, Which wyſſhe or iayenge is vtterlye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy the profeſſion yf the holye ghoſt, who ſayth &amp; wryteth al mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters both wel &amp; godly, &amp; ſo nedeth no pardon for the ſame. Yf the pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of Paul whych the catholiques alledge for purgatorye were to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame,<note place="margin">i. Cori. iii</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> queſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>onles were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles fyrſt placed &amp; vexed in the ſayd purgatory, ere they came to heauen. For why Paul talking in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely of preachers auoucheth that the fyre ſhal trye eche mans worke what it is, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were both me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule was not inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent after hys hence departure wyth Chriſte as he wyſſhed to bee For to bee placed and tormented
<pb facs="tcp:11242:77"/> in purgatore is not to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt So y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Lazarus &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thefe were not immediatli vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr deceaſe,<note place="margin">luk. 16.23</note> tho ne in paradiſe thother in Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s boſome, places of pleaſure, &amp; not of wofulnes (as purgatorie is. If Chriſtes talke in Mathew .v. con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning the extreme empriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of certayn, enforſed for purgatore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neyther ſoule maſſes ſacryfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ne prayers could enforce anye thyng to the raunſome and deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunce of them, who ar payned in the ſame. For theyr chriſte ſwereth they ſhal not come oute thenſe, tyl they payed the vttermoſt farthin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. What can prayer, ſacryfyce or maſſe auayle her, ſythe chriſte ſo exactly demaundeth the full pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of thee dett, as wythoute it the empryſoned ſhall not be fredo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med and delyuered? He ſpeake the of a place where iuſtice is execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and not mercee, that is hel and
<pb facs="tcp:11242:77"/> not purgatore. Oute of another ſayinge of Chriſte in the ſayd Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thew .xii. oure catholiques do ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue for purgatore but expuris ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatiuis &amp; therfore theyr argumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation beynge not formall is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge effectuall. The cauſe why oure aunciente wryters ſaye, they ſacrifyce and praye for thee dead, was not to delyuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne therby (For they ſacrificed and prayed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> patriarches prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes apoſtles alſo who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fit already in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; had no nede of theyr prayers or ſacrifices) but partely too declare thereby theyr charitee towarde the hence depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in wel wyſſhinge them &amp; ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring god thankes for theyr ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion &amp; endeles bleſſefulnes, partly to aſſure &amp; warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſuruyuers at the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of the good &amp; bleſful eſtate of the deceaſed, both of euerlaſtinge lyfe &amp; bodelye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection:
<pb facs="tcp:11242:78"/> To ſacryfyce Chriſtes body &amp; bloud eyther for the dead, or quycke, after the true meanyng of the foreſayd wryters, is namely to recite &amp; pray for the ſayd perſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in thoſe our prayers which we make at the receypt of the lordes ſupper, called otherwyſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſacryfyce of the lordes bodye and bloud, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is a reſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof &amp; not as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſolle maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers miſtake it, to vp offre the ſayd body &amp; bloud in very dede to clen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thee quycke: and too redeme and raunſome the deadde oute of purgatory wythal. For after thys lyfe ther is no purging ne ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t place. Therfore ſayth Cipria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the fyrſt treate agaynſt Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trian whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce departe ther is no place of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. here lyfe is ether forfetted or atteigned. Why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le we be here ſaith Chriſoſtome in hys ſecond homeli of Lazarus we
<pb facs="tcp:11242:78"/> haue good hope, but ſo ſoone as we ſhal hence departe, we ſhal not eyther repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or do awaye ſyn. The ſame Chriſoſtome in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two &amp; twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye ſermon to the people ſaith, ther be none occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of meriting after this lyfe. Who ſo (ſayth Ambroſe in the ii. chap. of hys boke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the goodnes of death) hath not here receyued remyſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſyn ſhall not receaue it ther. There is no place, ſayth Auſteyn in hys E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to macedonius, of correcti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our demeinour, but i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this life. For after this lyfe eche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall haue that whych he procured to him in thys, What can be more openlye &amp; dyrectly wrytten agaynſt the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyſh purgatorye, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the alledged auctoritees? why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do we mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn purgatorie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary both to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture &amp; auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wryters? But beit there were a purginge place wherin the hence departed ſolles be
<pb facs="tcp:11242:79"/> a mockedg &amp; blaſpheming of god is this, for the maſſer to praye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes prayer let thy wyll be done in earth &amp; yet contrary to goddes wyl to pray for the erectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce of hys ſacrifyce to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great hinderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; derogation of chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whych was ꝑfyted &amp; wrought at hys maieſtyes appoyntmente? What is to take the name of god in vayne, yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be not? &amp; ſo ſinneful What is to flocke &amp; deſpyſe god yf that be not? In reſpecte wherof maſſe prayer is reprocheful. Now to the fourth &amp; laſt part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe named doctrine, whych in conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration it teacheth &amp; ratifieth thee damnable ſynfulnes of the before mencioned partes of this ſolitary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſe exhorting and occaſionyng the laye people bothe to enbrace &amp; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſhip the ſame is fautie as thei be. For the doctryne of a ſynneful matter is ſynful as the matter ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue.
<pb facs="tcp:11242:79"/> Not onlye to ryot is ſynne, but the doctryne alſo therof &amp; the allu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re to the ſame, To ſteale &amp; to tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che or exhort to ſteale be bothe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faultes, Too ſynne &amp; to teache or moue to ſynne be bothe ſinnefull. Euen ſo to pryuat maſſe it &amp; to tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che &amp; motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo to do be both defaul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes exchewable, Here am I demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded wether I ſuppoſe the epyſtell and goſpel interplaced in the maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe to be godly &amp; approueable or no To the whyth demaunde thus I anſwere. The goſpell &amp; epyſtell yf they were not abuſed &amp; miſplaced were both godly and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable But for ſo moch as thei be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerted and placed in the pryuee maſſe to the furniture worſhip and comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dation therof, and for a couerte or cloke of the vngodlynes in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, they ſo miſuſed muſt nedes be ſynneful. Meate and drinke be good and receyueable but enpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned,
<pb facs="tcp:11242:80"/> they be nought &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>receaueable, &amp; poiſon theyr eaters &amp; drinkers, as the pure poyſon ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue doth, wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ar poiſoned: Right ſo gods worde merely of it ſelue is good &amp; frutful but abuſed vngodli, diſpleſing god &amp; e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pechi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the ſyn abuſion doth, wher w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is corrupted. An exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple &amp; eui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wherof we haue both in oure maſſing, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iuring wherin gods wordes be haynouſli abuſed. The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is no ſeruice ne worſhip whiche god ſo highly eſtemeth or ſo ſtrayt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly inioyneth to be obſerued, but be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge miſuſed is not only not ſerui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceable &amp; acceptable, but moch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo &amp; hateful to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bicau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe it is executed, not after but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his wyl &amp; therfore ſinfull and deteſtable before hym, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght vſage &amp; not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abuſage (as of al other maters) ſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> premiſſes. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:11242:80"/> god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded both ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and holy daies to be obſerued, howbeit he ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly by hys ꝓphetes auoucheth he hath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hate &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſpect of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, for he bad the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of theyr abuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which he inhibited I hate ſaithe he by his ꝓphete A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos, &amp; abhorre your holy dayes &amp; wher ye ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce me whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye come toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther I wol not acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt it. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by hys ꝓphete Eſay .i. he ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth thus, I abhorre your ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe I may not away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your newmones your ſabathes &amp; ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne daies. &amp;c Note this dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, god ſaith not I abhorre ye for your abuſyng of the holy dayes nor he ſayth I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre your abuſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy dayes, but I abhorre your holy daies, he ſaith not I abhorre ye for your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe newmoones ſabba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes &amp; ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne dayes, nor he ſayth I abhorre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe
<pb facs="tcp:11242:81"/> new moones ſabathes &amp; ſolemne daies, wherby he doth vs to wete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth not only hate &amp; deteſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abuſers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there abuſage of hys commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ſeruice &amp; worſhippe, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice alſo &amp; worſhip ſelue as an inhybyted ſynne practyſed of man, &amp; forged of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl, and not as an honour inioyned apꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; deuyſed of him, &amp; through his grace put in practice of man. In conſideracion wherof god na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſaide holy dayes newe moones ſabbathes not hys, but youres, it to wete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes whom he ſpooke vnto. For nothing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is ſinfull (as eche abuſed mater is) ought to be fathered of God the fountane &amp; authore not of ſinful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes but of goodnes only.<note place="margin">Iacob. i</note> Which matere is by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane of his abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage not a parte only, but throug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hlie faultie.<note place="margin">i. Corin. v</note> A litle leauen (ſayth) Paule ſowreth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole lumpe of
<pb facs="tcp:11242:81"/> dowe. Wherby he doth vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as othere abuſed mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters be not a part only, but entier<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and throughly vicious and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, ſo the preſt maſſe is in like ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner as wel in his doctryne, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other hys eſſential partes. Sethe (good reader) there is no portyon of the popyſſhe pryuat maſſe that doth not hyghly diſpleaſe god as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e pugnant to hys wrytten worde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd derogatorye to hys honour, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnoy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as noyous both to hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ody and ſoule: I beſech the with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll poſſible endeuour exchewe it &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o maner wyſe, accepte it as ether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pproueable eyther els a ſuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le matter. If gods honour ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccaſion and moue vs to the vtter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efuſal and auoydau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof, let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s wel reſpecte the great benefyt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd commodytye that redounethe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her vpon. If nether gods glorye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e our profyt, can enforce vs to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:82"/> premiſſes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſh beeſtes, which, though not for godes glori, yet for theyr own, pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyt, ar ledde willingly hither &amp; thi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther. We reſort to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſely to ſerue god therin, not wyth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſeruice, which he i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hibiteth &amp; diſlyketh, but with his own alone which he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth &amp; accepteth. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no maner ſeruice ought to be freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that alone which is both openlye and truly fonded vpon gods wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten worde. Why then is not the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prieſte pryuee Maſſe abandoned and aboliſhed quyte out of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is not quadrant but variant to the ſayd word, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che doth not ratify &amp; eſtabliſh bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inuert &amp; ſubuert the ryght inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion &amp; vſage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes body &amp; bloud (as is heretofo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re argued at ful). And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> romt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therof why is not the communio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:82"/> frequented? Is not the ſayd com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion a new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as chriſt ſelue ſaythe in Luke .xxii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Can a man therfore not ſynfully but ley<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulli alter the order therof? No ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>relye. For as S. Paule ſayth it is not leyful to excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">Gala. iii</note> moche leſſe gods wyl legacye &amp; teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doo we reteygne accepte &amp; vſe ſolytare maſſe? Which is an vnſitting exchange of the commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion (the lordes Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacye). Is not the ſayd communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on a Sacrament of charitye and loue? In conſyderation whereof it is not to receaued of one alone, but of manye at ones. For chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyſteth in many &amp; not in one alone. Why then vſe we ſtyll thee prieſte maſſe? whyche is rather an vnion then a communion and an argument rather of hate and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of loue and vnite. For therin the prieſt vncharitably fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth
<pb facs="tcp:11242:83"/> hym ſelue from the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregatyon, as one ſeuered not in place alone, but in harte alſo from the ſame. It is no marueyl that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt is had in great hate and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t emong hys pariſhioners ſeith he ſo vncharitabli taketh, ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth, and drinketh al alone, diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering and ſequeſtring him ſelue from hys accompanable parriſhi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oners, leſt they wold communyca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te (as charitable godlynes requy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth (wyth hym. It is a lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table ſyght to behold the great &amp; vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lerable vncharitablenes whyche our pryuate maſſing preſtes ſhew toward theyr partiſhioners. Vere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly (as me ſeamethe) theyr pryuate maſſyng is no ſmal occaſyon ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of. By reaſon as the communyon engendereth orderly lowe, ſo thee pryuate maſſynge hate in the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenters of the ſame: For why as
<pb facs="tcp:11242:83"/> they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary in nature, ſo they be in effect &amp; operation. Wherfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the ſayd maſſinge is not be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of any, but is to be diſvſed of eche chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Who ought to en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deuour him ſelue to be charitable and not vncharitable.<note place="margin">i. Cori. 10</note> We ought (ſayth Paul) to eate al of one lofe,<note place="margin">i. Cori. 10</note> and drinke al of one cup, we ough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te (as the ſame Paule wolleth vs) aſſemble togethers to the receypt of the communion,<note place="margin">1. Cori: 11.</note> and one to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it orderly after another: Theſe premiſſes cannot be accompliſhed and veryfyed in the pryuate maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, where the prieſt ſeuerally all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone hath hys loofe &amp; eateth it alo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, wher ther is none aſſemble aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled togethers to receaue thee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, but to gaſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes receypt &amp; doynge, where none receaueth the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> order<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly one after another, but vnorder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly one alone. Wherfore thee ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:11242:84"/> maſſe is to be diſcontinued &amp; aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned. For whi he is accurſed who ſo teacheth eyther in woorde, dede or ioynctlye in both, another doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne in relygion, then that whych Paul learned vs,<note place="margin">Gala. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as he hym ſelue recordeth the ſame. We muſte not do what we lyſte, but what god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundethe vs, as it is wrytten in Deuteronomy .xii. For why oure carnall reaſon &amp; entendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes be merely repugnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, both to his ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>enges &amp; doynges, &amp; ſo diſpleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and hateful to him. The ſenſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe (ſayth Paule) is enmytee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt God.<note place="margin">Roma. 8.</note> In caſe we moughte worſhip god as we lyſt, Why dyd he appoynt &amp; preſcribe vs a <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te order to worſhippe him withal? Yf we mought ſittingly honoure hym after our wyl &amp; fantaſy: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eche made worſhyp were ſyttinge and ieyful, and ſo conſequentelye ther were none ydolatree at al, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:11242:84"/> were there no dyfference betwexte oures and thee Turkes, Iewes Paynymes, Ethnikes, and other miſcreantes religion, For they be onely differenced by Goddes wryt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten woorde. If we moughte order chriſtes ſupper after our arbitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then why dyd he inſtitute &amp; preſcribe vs a trade and order to be obſerued in the celebratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of?<note place="margin">1. Cori. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Why dyd Paule reproue and blame thee Corinthians for theyr diſorder &amp; abuſage of the ſame? Ar not wee named chriſtians for that we ought to profeſſe and geue ful credence to his ſayinges and prac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſe, and enbrace hys doyinges, as followable and beleueable? But howe doo we anſwere to our name and profeſſion in our ſolita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie maſſing? wherin we do not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not enſue chriſtes practyſe and order, but throughly ſubuert and
<pb facs="tcp:11242:85"/> inuerte the ſame concernynge the adminiſtration of his ſupper Are we not called faythful for that we ought to grounde al our religion vpon our fayth? whych fayth iſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth only from Gods wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word, as Paule recordeth,<note place="margin">Roma. 10</note> otherwyſe no true fayth. But how can we be in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dede as we be named, yf we admit and frequente as wee doo, to thee greate and vnſufferable empeche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente bothe of Chriſtes honoure and our ſolles ſaluation, the preſt preuye maſſe? whych is variant to gods worde. Therfore as it is an vnfaythful, ſo as ſynneful miſdede For that which is wrought wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fayth is ſynne,<note place="margin">Roma, 10</note> as Paul ſaith: Ace we not ſtraytelye inioyned of God vtterly to abandon, &amp; auoyd all ydolatrye? How do we obſerue and accompliſhe this his iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, whyle we enbrace and accepte the ſayde maſſe? whych is a made
<pb facs="tcp:11242:85"/> worſhyppe of God, and ſo ydola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye. For the worſhyp of any phan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taſye entent conceypt and ymage, or of any other matter elſe, forged of mans brayne wythout goddes wrytten word, is queſtionles ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye? Hereto accordeth Hierome (who vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the laſt of Hieremye on thys verſe And they put theyr y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols in the houſe. etc, wrytethe in, ſorte thus) not only the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iudas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in Gods temple an ydoll y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, whereof we rede in the fyrſt of Ezechtel, but now ſtyll in gods houſe (whych by interpretation is the congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) or in the hart of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleuers, is placed an ydol, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer any new doctrine is forged, and after the law adored and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhypped in the ſecrete. And vpon the twentye of Ezechyel the ſayd, Hierome calleth the inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and deuyſes of the phyloſophers and herytyques, the Egyptia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ydols.
<pb facs="tcp:11242:86"/> Auncient vſage in other matters of relygion ſemeth to be of moche force &amp; importau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> accepta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; eſtabliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of any ſoch ſembla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble matter, but her in our pryuate maſſe matter the ſayd vſage is no thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g eſtemed (To ſure an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I feare me of oure parcialitee in ſcripture matters) Was not chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes own adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per the fyrſt original vſage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of?<note place="margin">Mat. xxvi</note> and ſo the auncienteſt? wherin none alone but ſoundrye ioinctly togethers dyd communicate? In the prematiue church it was both obſerued and enacted that all the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled ſhuld communicate wyth thee prieſte or miniſter, as it doth wel appere in Gracian de conſecra. diſtinct .i. in the canon de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whyche is fathered of the Apoſtles, in thee Canon E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus fathered of Anacletus, &amp; de conſecra. diſtinc .ii. in the canon
<pb facs="tcp:11242:86"/> peracta, Calixtus thus wryttethe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is done, let eche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate, &amp; then who woll not to be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate. This thee Apoſtles enacted thys doth the Romyſhe churche hold &amp; obſerue. Note thys that Calixtus doth not onli declare that it is his wyl &amp; commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t al they who be preſent at the communion time ſhuld communicate, els to be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municate, But the apoſtles decree &amp; the vſage of the Romiſhe church alſo. Ther be (ſaith Eraſmus vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pſalme, Quam dilectaberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula) who requyre in thee Maſſe a communion, In dede I graunt ſo it was inſtituted of Chriſt and ſo it was in thee olde tyme obſerued Albert in hys boke of thee Maſſe miſteries, recordeth it was fyrſt in wont that al the togethers aſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled perſones in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church did com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municat eche day, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could not be
<pb facs="tcp:11242:87"/> obſerued, it was decreed that on eche ſondaye al the hole congrega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion ſhuld communicate, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this neyther could be obſerued, it was decreed that thryſe in the yeare, at Eaſter, Whytſondaye, and Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maſſe, the communion ſhuld be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of the whole congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys could nether be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued it was enacted that ones in the yeare the ſayde communion ſhuld be receaued of the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregation. Here we may learne of Albert that in the primatiue chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che all thee whole congregation dyd communicate eche daye ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netly togethers. Further in caſe we wold wel and earneſtly reſpect the conſyderatyon of our repayre to the church, &amp; what alſo is of the maſſer reported oute of hys maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe boke at thee celebration of thee communion: We mought wel vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtande that the ſayd communi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:11242:87"/> ſhuld alway be receyued of a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paygne and not of one alone. Do we not (I praye ye) repayre to the churche, as to the common place, wherein we ſhulde make common prayers nothing excuting pryuat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly but all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly? Saynt Paule auoucheth,<note place="margin">i. Cori. 14</note> nothinge ought to be executed in thee churche, but that which redowneth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> edyfying &amp; behoue of the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo that as the churche is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon place, ſo the prayers therin ſhulde be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, ſo the celebration of the communion muſt be common, and not pryuate, as the wordes of the maſſe canon reported after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion do wel declare, whych be thees followynge. That, that we haue receyued by the mouth, lord graunt we may receaue wyth hart purpoſely that ther may be made vnto vs an euerlaſting remedy of the body &amp; bloud of our lord Ieſu
<pb facs="tcp:11242:88"/> chriſt. It is not ſayd I, but we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue receaued. The prieſt as here ſo in other places ſaith not I but we eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whyle he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municateth all alo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, wherby it is gatherable y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſhuld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat not ſeuerally alone but iounctlye wyth others. For wee importeth a multitude &amp; not a ſingularitee. Some ther be who deme the ſolitary maſſing an indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; conſequently a ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able matter. Wel thoughe it were ſo, as queſtionles it is not: Howbe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>it for ſo moch as we haue vtterlye renounced the Romſſhe biſhop w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al his vſurped autorite, we ought of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d on ther wyth the pryuate maſſe, whych he forged &amp; fathered, leſſe we through reteyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te &amp; vſage therof, be occaſio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to reſume &amp; agayn enbrace the ſayd byſhop withal his vnſytting &amp; prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed authorite. For vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blable conſyderation,<note place="margin">leui. xviii</note> God inhibi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:11242:88"/> the Iſraelites the vſage of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptyans ceremonies, wherewith they had heretofore bene enfected, albeit ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by al lykelyho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de were indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g (ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle reder) Ihertofor haue moch what veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly gaynſayd the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uie maſſe &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned here as dete<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtable erroneouſe &amp; blaſphemous: Howbeit I truſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wolſte accepte this my labour, enbracing &amp; enſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing my doctrine therin, as enſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; credible, ſyth it te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not to gods diſhonour but to his honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, not to thine empecheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t but to thy great comodite, not to the hin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ouerthrow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but to the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dreſſe recouery &amp; furtherance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true maſſe, otherwiſe named the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munion, whych ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſo highly eſtemed and ſo ofte frequented as of neceſſytye it oughte, wythoute the prieſte maſſe be hated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted. For bothe it and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion cannot be iounctly regar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded.
<pb facs="tcp:11242:89"/> Whoſo loueth thee one muſt nedes hate thother, for why they be mere contraries. But how can thee prieſte maſſe be hadde in worthy hate? yf her abominacyon were not at full dyſcloſed? In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect wherof, thou ſeeſt how nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe ſhuld be both gayne ſayed and condemned as hereſye, and abandoned as ydolatrye. God of hys mercye graunt vs all to learne, loue credyte and mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne hys truth and lyue thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11242:89"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11242:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:11242:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
